<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>life on</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/tags/life/</link><description>Recent content in life on</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/tags/life/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Career and Life Advice from Polly</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/notes/ideas/Career-and-Life-Advice-From-Polly/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/notes/ideas/Career-and-Life-Advice-From-Polly/</guid><description>Career and Life Advice From Polly Dear Polly,
For most of my 20s, I dreamed about doing my Ph.D. I worked a couple of well-paying, practical office jobs that I hated, and I was miserable. I paid off my loans. I saved. Every few months, I would have an existential crisis where I would try to think of the career paths that might lead me to happiness, and every time I was convinced that doing a Ph.</description></item><item><title>Hanging Out With My Brother</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/notes/ideas/Hanging-Out-With-My-Brother/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/notes/ideas/Hanging-Out-With-My-Brother/</guid><description>Link &amp;ldquo;Hell is other people, but life is other people if you care about them enough.&amp;rdquo;
The main character in red is shown chatting with his brother in blue about what&amp;rsquo;s bothering him. He has been working on a theory of the [[meaning of life]]. It describes the [[self]] as dependent on our relationship with others; it&amp;rsquo;s all connected. There&amp;rsquo;s a notion of distance in his diagram of these interconnected relationships, which he claims doesn&amp;rsquo;t matter as much as their quality.</description></item><item><title>Horizon</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/notes/ideas/Horizon/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/notes/ideas/Horizon/</guid><description>quotes &amp;ldquo;It was important to Walsh that a human being, not a rover or a probe, first saw the bottom of the Pacific. &amp;ldquo;You can&amp;rsquo;t surprise a machine,&amp;rdquo; he said to me. And it is this capacity to appreciate the unknown, to be surprised by it, he believes, that will always set the human explorer apart from the machine. The moment of surprise informs you emphatically that the way you once imagined the world is not the way it is.</description></item></channel></rss>