<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>learning on</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/tags/learning/</link><description>Recent content in learning on</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/tags/learning/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Education at Bat</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/notes/learning/Education-at-Bat/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/notes/learning/Education-at-Bat/</guid><description>When Harvard Graduate School of Education Professor David Perkins looked back at his childhood little league and &amp;ldquo;backyard baseball&amp;rdquo; experiences, he found the perfect metaphor for the set of teaching concepts presented in his 2008 book, Making Learning Whole: How Seven Principles of Teaching Can Transform Education .
Asked in an interview with Usable Knowledge to describe how he would like educators to work with his ideas, Perkins says, “They should get a rough sense of the ideas and start using them….</description></item><item><title>why to memorize poems</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/notes/Poems/why-we-should-memorize-poems/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/notes/Poems/why-we-should-memorize-poems/</guid><description>Article Source Much of our daily lives would be dizzyingly unrecognizable to people living a hundred years ago: what we wear and what we eat, how we travel, how we communicate, how we while away our leisure time. But, surely, our occasional attempts to memorize a poem would feel familiar to them—those inhabitants of a heyday of verse memorization. Little has changed. They, too, in committing a poem to memory, underwent a predictable gamut of frustrations: the pursuit of stubbornly elusive phrases, the inner hammering of rote repetition, tantalizing tip-of-the-tongue stammerings, confident forward marches that finish in an abrupt amnesiac’s cul-de-sac.</description></item></channel></rss>