<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Phil's Digital Garden on</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/</link><description>Recent content in Phil's Digital Garden on</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title/><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ABCD/ABCD-Project/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ABCD/ABCD-Project/</guid><description>#TODO
finish notes/statistics/Statistical-Rethinking Read 2021-baseline-fmri-abcd.pdf Important ideas notes/statistics/statistical-power notes/statistics/effect-size linear-regression Common-statistical-tests papers [[2021-baseline-fmri-abcd.pdf]] [[2021-abcd-meaningful-associations.pdf]] [[Recruiting the ABCD Sample.pdf]] [[Thinking Clearly About Correlations and Causation - Graphical Causal Models for Observational Data]] [[covid-depression-teens-2021.pdf]]</description></item><item><title/><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/health/Health-Journal/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/health/Health-Journal/</guid><description>Topics sleep physical health mental health meditation Happiness Andrew Huberman&amp;rsquo;s ideal day</description></item><item><title/><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/backfire-effect/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/backfire-effect/</guid><description>Once something is added to your collection of notes/ideas/belief s, you protect it from harm. You do this instinctively and unconsciously when confronted with attitude-inconsistent information. Just as notes/ideas/confirmation-bias shields you when you actively seek information, the backfire effect defends you when the information seeks you, when it blindsides you. Coming or going, you stick to your beliefs instead of questioning them. When someone tries to correct you, tries to dilute your misconceptions, it backfires and strengthens those misconceptions instead.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/neuro/fmri/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/neuro/fmri/</guid><description>#flashcards
about brain images voxels are the pixels of brain images. They are 3-D, measured as cubic millimetres.
temporal vs spatial resolution: structural images are captured using smaller voxels and look nicer as a result.
in functional imaging, because we want to take a picture of the brain at a faster frequency, we must sacrifice some spatial resolution for higher temporal resolution
What makes fMRI analysis complicated? Noise due to head motion and other artifacts (e.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/Poems/Emily-Dickinson/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/Poems/Emily-Dickinson/</guid><description>Emily Dickinson 435 Much madness is divinest Sense</description></item><item><title/><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/psychology/constant-practice/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/psychology/constant-practice/</guid><description>Yesterday I snapped at my puppy. He was having a wild case of the zoomies in the backyard and trying to rip my favorite sweatshirt apart with his teeth. He’d already left a nice bite mark on my wrist and it was raining hard, which doubly irritated me since I hate the rain. I raised my voice and when that didn’t work (why would it work??) I carried him inside. Once he was calm five minutes later I felt completely ridiculous.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/relationships/Do-I-Self-Sabotage-When-It-Comes-to-Dating/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/relationships/Do-I-Self-Sabotage-When-It-Comes-to-Dating/</guid><description>Dear Polly,
I’m a 28-year-old woman who has only dated one person, a man 14 years older than me, for over six years in my early 20s. I haven’t been with anyone else before or after that, apart from kissing a few people I’ve met on dating apps. Those dates never went anywhere, mostly mutually. It’s been over two years now, and I’m starting to feel like something’s got to change if I’m ever going to be close to anyone again.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/Expectation/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/Expectation/</guid><description>Expected Value The long-run average value of a discrete random variable, say $X$, with support $c$ is $$E(X) = \sum_{c{\in}A}{c}{P(X=c)}$$.
Properties of Expected Values $E(X+Y) = E(X) + E(Y)$ $E(aX) = aE(X)$ $E(g(X)) = \sum_{c{\in}A}{g(c)}{P(X=c)}$ where $A$ is the support of $X$ $E(UV) = EU{\cdot}EV$ if $U$ and $V$ are independent.</description></item><item><title/><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/machine-learning/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/machine-learning/</guid><description>Table of Contents general ideas linear algebra bias-variance tradeoff cross validation Gradient Descent Supervised Learning algorithms linear regression logistic regression support vector machines decision tree random forests Unsupervised Learning algorithms k-means clustering PCA metrics sensitivity specificity accuracy</description></item><item><title>25 Lessons by Mandy</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/25-Lessons-Learned-by-Mandy/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/25-Lessons-Learned-by-Mandy/</guid><description>25 Lessons Learned by Mandy I wrote these thoughts about turning twenty-five this year, and realized both how far I have come and how much I have left to learn. This blog is meant to be my creative outlet, and also want to be able to read the pieces I wrote in the future and see growth. If I don’t look back at these and cringe a little in five years, I am living my life wrong :).</description></item><item><title>36 Questions</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/relationships/36-questions/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/relationships/36-questions/</guid><description>Some fun questions to ask on a date.
Set I Given the choice of anyone in the world, whom would you want as a dinner guest? Would you like to be famous? In what way? Before making a telephone call, do you ever rehearse what you are going to say? Why? What would constitute a “perfect” day for you?</description></item><item><title>A Life of One's Own</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/psychology/A-Life-of-Ones-Own/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/psychology/A-Life-of-Ones-Own/</guid><description>Synopsis &amp;lsquo;Joanna Field&amp;rsquo; was born and educated in England. At the age of 11 she wanted to be a naturalist or a painter. At 18 her interest turned from wild nature to human nature, and she began to train for work with very young children; but feeling the need for deeper study she went on to take a degree in psychology and physiology at London University. After this she worked as an investigator in industrial psychology and then held a Rockefeller fellowship in the U.</description></item><item><title>A Network Theory of Mental Disorders</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/mental-health/a-network-theory-of-mental-disorders/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/mental-health/a-network-theory-of-mental-disorders/</guid><description>Summary An alternative conception of mental health where the disorder arises from direct interactions between symptoms. It&amp;rsquo;s a framework that causally connects symptoms of psychopathology to biological, psychological, and societal mechanisms. If the interplay of these mechanisms are strong enough, then a feedback loop is created that makes the symptoms self-sustaining, i.e. the network gets stuck in a disordered state. &amp;ldquo;The network theory holds that this is a general feature of mental health , which can therefore be understood as alternative stable states of strongly connected symptom networks.</description></item><item><title>A Pledge for Lovers</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/relationships/A-Pledge-for-Lovers/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/relationships/A-Pledge-for-Lovers/</guid><description>Source : From the School of Life
The surest indicator of the success of a relationship is not whether or not there are arguments, moments of fury, stretches of loneliness or incidents of betrayal. It is, quite simply, whether or not two people want to be together.
If they do, and if they firmly know this of themselves and of the other, then pretty much every obstacle can be overcome.</description></item><item><title>ABCD pre-registration</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ABCD/ABCD-pre-registration/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ABCD/ABCD-pre-registration/</guid><description>Pre-registration for the ABCD Study In order to make hypothesis registration as easy as possible this platform supports the structured generation of hypothesis. This includes the definition of the hypothesis with variable selection and data transformations. Additionally, DEAP provides sample texts for the following sections that may be part of your hypothesis registration:
Sampling Plan Design Plan Analysis Plan Analysis Scripts We suggest to use the Open Science Foundation ( OSF ) framework to register hypothesis.</description></item><item><title>ABCD pre-registration</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ABCD/ABCD-Study/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ABCD/ABCD-Study/</guid><description>On recruiting the sample, see: ==Recruiting the ABCD Sample==</description></item><item><title>accuracy</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/accuracy/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/accuracy/</guid><description/></item><item><title>addiction</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/mental-health/addiction/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/mental-health/addiction/</guid><description>Juggling my Children, Their Alcoholic Sitter and My Own Sobriety Gabor Mate on Addiction &amp;ldquo;I stumbled upon your YouTube channel a few days ago. I just wanted to say thank you and let you know that your videos are being shown to drug addicts at a facility in Dayton, OH where they are making a real impact on our patients. This area has been ravaged by heroine addiction and I work as a counselor helping people turn their lives around.</description></item><item><title>adolescence</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/mental-health/adolescence/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/mental-health/adolescence/</guid><description/></item><item><title>adulthood</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/psychology/adulthood/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/psychology/adulthood/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Adverse Childhood Experiences</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/mental-health/Adverse-Childhood-Experiences/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/mental-health/Adverse-Childhood-Experiences/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Again</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/Poems/Again/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/Poems/Again/</guid><description>God’s knocking at the bedroom door again. You redress yourself in reason but the devilish grin isn’t coming off as easily as before. You tell me we’re pushing it, you say we asked for forgiveness last time. But I remind you that he’s a professional, that we keep him in business by asking over and over and over again.
Me</description></item><item><title>agendaless attention</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/psychology/agendaless-attention/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/psychology/agendaless-attention/</guid><description>My understanding of agendaless perception draws on my understanding of perception with an agenda, which was a main topic of my work in artificial intelligence .
In a well-practiced task, you know what to look for where , because you know what the things you see mean. This can be verified with gaze tracking: experimental subjects focus their attention tightly in predictable, task-relevant places.
This makes me think about the ethics of classifying things, and in general the impact of trying to classify everything on society and culture</description></item><item><title>All Minus One</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/All-Minus-One/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/All-Minus-One/</guid><description>Source Mill’s main concern was not government censorship. It was the stultifying consequences of social conformity, of a culture where deviation from a prescribed set of opinions is punished through peer pressure and the fear of ostracism. “Protection, therefore, against the tyranny of the magistrate is not enough,” he wrote. “There needs protection also against the tyranny of the prevailing opinion and feeling”. Mill saw people even as brilliant as Charles Darwin living in fear of the response their views would provoke.</description></item><item><title>Already Free</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/books/Already-Free/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/books/Already-Free/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Alzheimer's disease</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/neuro/alzheimers/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/neuro/alzheimers/</guid><description> Most common form of dementia , a progressive brain disorder that occurs more frequently at later stages of life. The primary symptoms of dementia are decline in memory and other cognitive functions.</description></item><item><title>Am I Too Picky To Find Love</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/relationships/Am-I-Too-Picky-To-Find-Love/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/relationships/Am-I-Too-Picky-To-Find-Love/</guid><description>A great Ask Polly piece. Worth thinking about in the context of notes/relationships/relationships .
Dear Polly,
Brace yourself for one of the most conceited querents you’ll ever encounter. At the blossoming age of 26, I’m here writing to you about the quest of trying to ‘have it all’ romantically. Growing up I was a major tomboy, a fashion anarchist, and a borderline spinster-in-training. I didn’t (and still won’t!) wear make-up, I didn’t care about popular fashion trends, I was incredibly nerdy, and although I had the odd crush here or there, I really wasn’t concerned with finding love, or a boyfriend.</description></item><item><title>ambition</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/ambition/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/ambition/</guid><description/></item><item><title>American Bike Project - What I Learned</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/health/abp-learned/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/health/abp-learned/</guid><description>American Bike Project: What I Learned National Geographic Travel photographer Tyler Metcalfe recently quit his job and sold off his possessions to embark on an epic solo adventure of cross-country cycling that has dealt him many ups and downs.
With only a hundred miles left to go in my cross-country bike tour, I began to imagine how my trip might end. I assumed that the final days of my journey would involve an easy ride over the scenic foothills of Washington’s Olympic Peninsula, which would eventually give way to a gentle path leading down to a beach where I would finally dip my bike tires in the Pacific Ocean.</description></item><item><title>American Bike Project - Where to Sleep</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/health/abp-sleep/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/health/abp-sleep/</guid><description>American Bike Project: Where to Sleep If travel experiences were judged solely based on the number of different places a traveler slept during a single trip, bike touring might win a prize as the best form of travel. Though I don’t believe this is how a travel experience should be judged (and I have had some of my greatest travel experiences by simply planting myself in a single neighborhood for the duration of a trip), I do believe bike touring offers an extremely unique form of travel where a lot can be seen over a short period of time.</description></item><item><title>American Bike Project Gear</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/health/abp-gear/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/health/abp-gear/</guid><description>Source daypack: hyperlite mountain gear daybreak stove: snow peak bipod tent knife headlamp watch bike: Surly Cross-Check ($899) / Disc Trucker ($1749) panniers: Ortlieb (x4) handlebar bag: camera, snacks, maps Food and Water: For the most part, I’ll only be carrying one to two days’ worth of food and water at a time. During the eastern portion of my trip, I’ll be passing through small towns several times a day, where I’ll load up on food items like peanut butter, bagels, cured meats, avocados, granola, and nuts.</description></item><item><title>amygdala</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/neuro/amygdala/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/neuro/amygdala/</guid><description>Brain region typically associated with threat detection, anxiety, fear response.</description></item><item><title>An Instruction Manual to Oneself</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/relationships/An-Instruction-Manual-to-Oneself/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/relationships/An-Instruction-Manual-to-Oneself/</guid><description>An Instruction Manual to Oneself Most machines of any degree of complexity are offered to us with an instruction manual, a guide to how an unfamiliar technology works, what we can expect from it, how to get the best out of it and how to interpret its signals – the assumption being that it will be so much easier and less enraging to deal with the machine when we have taken some time systematically and patiently to learn how it operates.</description></item><item><title>anki</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/learning/anki/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/learning/anki/</guid><description>A useful tool for learning that exploits spaced repetition and the learning curve (discovered by Ebbinghaus) to effectively remember things.</description></item><item><title>ANOVA</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/ANOVA/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/ANOVA/</guid><description/></item><item><title>arguing well</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/arguing-well/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/arguing-well/</guid><description>via [[Daniel Dennett]] You should attempt to re-express your target’s position so clearly, vividly, and fairly that your target says, “Thanks, I wish I’d thought of putting it that way. You should list any points of agreement (especially if they are not matters of general or widespread agreement). You should mention anything you have learned from your target. Only then are you permitted to say so much as a word of rebuttal or criticism.</description></item><item><title>Autoencoders</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/Autoencoders/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/Autoencoders/</guid><description>What are autoencoders?
They are a special kind of feedforward network with two components, the encoder and decoder.
Encoders learn to generate a latent representation of the data.
Decoders learns to use these latent representations to reconstruct the input data as close as possible to the original.
Autoencoders are unsupervised learning techniques that extract meaningful features from the input based on the type of autoencoder you use (e.g. sparse autoencoder or denoising autoencoders).</description></item><item><title>Bayes All the Way Up</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/bayes-all-the-way-up/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/bayes-all-the-way-up/</guid><description>Bayes Theorem is an equation for calculating certain kinds of conditional probabilities. For something so obscure, it’s attracted a surprisingly wide fanbase, including doctors , environmental scientists , economists , bodybuilders , fen-dwellers , and international smugglers . Eventually the hype reached the point where there was both a Bayesian cabaret and a Bayesian choir , popular books using Bayes’ Theorem to prove both the existence and the nonexistence of God, and even Bayesian dating advice .</description></item><item><title>Bayes Factor</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/Bayes-factor/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/Bayes-factor/</guid><description>A video introduction</description></item><item><title>Bayesian statistics</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/Bayesian-Statistics/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/Bayesian-Statistics/</guid><description>Allen Downey, on why it doesn&amp;rsquo;t make sense to compare Frequentist statistical results with Bayesian results: You can’t compare results from Bayesian and Frequentist methods because the results are different kinds of things. Results from Frequentist methods are generally a ==point estimate==, a ==confidence interval==, and/or a ==p-value==. Each of those results is an answer to a different question: #flashcards
point estimate: If I have to pick a single value, which one minimizes a particular cost function under a particular set of constraints?</description></item><item><title>bdnf</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/health/bdnf/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/health/bdnf/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Be the Change You Want to See</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/relationships/Be-The-Change-You-Want-to-See/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/relationships/Be-The-Change-You-Want-to-See/</guid><description>Be the Change You Want To See We spend a lot of time trying to change other people. There is, after all, so much wrong with them: they’re selfish, arrogant, bullying, weak, cold, needy and so on.
So we try to point this out – and often meet with resistance, denial or sheer indifference. This can be very agitating and hence renders us cross and severe. Why won’t people take our lessons on board?</description></item><item><title>beliefs</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/belief/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/belief/</guid><description/></item><item><title>bias</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/bias/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/bias/</guid><description/></item><item><title>bias-variance tradeoff</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/bias-variance-tradeoff/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/bias-variance-tradeoff/</guid><description>variance and bias refer to under and overfitting on the data.
Wikipedia on the bias-variance tradeoff: bias is error from erroneous assumptions in the ==model/learning algorithm== [e.g. using linear models when the data is non-linear -&amp;gt; high bias, more generalizable; not using enough predictors or predictors that may be important to the outcome -&amp;gt; high bias]. High bias causes the model to miss the relevant relations between features and target outputs, which leads to ==underfitting==.</description></item><item><title>binomial distribution</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/binomial-distribution/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/binomial-distribution/</guid><description>The binomial distribution is the generalized version of the Bernoulli distribution where instead of calculating the probability of success of a single event, we want the probability of $k$ successes in $n$ trials (in the Bernoulli $n=1$).
The probability of $k$ successful outcomes over $n$ trials is given by : $$P_k = {n \choose k}{p^k}{(1-p)^{n-k}}$$
The binomial distribution is the most consistent distribution - it maximizes entropy - given these constraints:</description></item><item><title>BOLD signal</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/neuro/BOLD-signal/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/neuro/BOLD-signal/</guid><description/></item><item><title>bootstrap method</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/bootstrap-method/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/bootstrap-method/</guid><description>repeatedly resampling the data with replacement, and then using the distribution of the statistic computed on those samples as a surrogate for the sampling distribution of the statistic</description></item><item><title>burnout</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/mental-health/burnout/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/mental-health/burnout/</guid><description> By Now, Burnout is a Given</description></item><item><title>butterfly effect</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/butterfly-effect/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/butterfly-effect/</guid><description>The sensitive dependence on initial conditions whereby a small change in a deterministic nonlinear system can result in large differences in a later state.
Coined by mathematician Edward Lorenz. He used the example of a tornado&amp;rsquo;s initial starting point and the path it follows, saying that where it goes can vary widely because of minor perturbations such as the flapping of a butterfly&amp;rsquo;s wings weeks earlier.
The phrase refers to the idea that a butterfly&amp;rsquo;s wings might create tiny changes in the atmosphere that may ultimately alter the path of a tornado or delay, accelerate or even prevent the occurrence of a tornado in another location.</description></item><item><title>caffeine</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/health/caffeine/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/health/caffeine/</guid><description>#flashcards
How does caffeine delay sleep?::It delays the binding of adenosine. The adenosine still builds up though, and once the caffeine in our body has been fully metabolized, the adenosine receptors are suddenly flooded and we experience the &amp;ldquo;crash&amp;rdquo;.</description></item><item><title>career</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/career/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/career/</guid><description>An article on the problem of having too many options: The Trouble With Optionality A poem by Carl Dennis : The God Who Loves You See also: Career and Life Advice From Polly</description></item><item><title>Career and Life Advice from Polly</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/Career-and-Life-Advice-From-Polly/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/Career-and-Life-Advice-From-Polly/</guid><description>Career and Life Advice From Polly Dear Polly,
For most of my 20s, I dreamed about doing my Ph.D. I worked a couple of well-paying, practical office jobs that I hated, and I was miserable. I paid off my loans. I saved. Every few months, I would have an existential crisis where I would try to think of the career paths that might lead me to happiness, and every time I was convinced that doing a Ph.</description></item><item><title>causal inference</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/causal-inference/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/causal-inference/</guid><description>Introduction Something counterintuitive about correlation Causation does not necessarily imply correlation .
Mixtape example: the sailor who is moving the rudder in response to the wind. Because she is responding to the wind, you don&amp;rsquo;t see any relationship between the movement of the rudder and the direction of the boat.
Another current example: social distancing and masking. We social distance and mask in response to the pandemic. But we don&amp;rsquo;t see the case count go down, we just see cases not change.</description></item><item><title>causal salad</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/causal-salad/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/causal-salad/</guid><description/></item><item><title>causality</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/causality/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/causality/</guid><description>References
Conditioning on a collider selection distortion effect casual inference: two-variable designs</description></item><item><title>Chapter 8 Statistical Rethinking</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/Chapter-8-Statistical-Rethinking/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/Chapter-8-Statistical-Rethinking/</guid><description>To setup a categorical interaction (e.g. the association between GDP and ruggedness is conditional on the continent [Africa or not]), include index variables in the model so that we can create different slopes (betas) and intercepts conditioned on each category.
For a continuous interaction, we need to make the slope(s) (beta(s)) themselves conditional on another variable; the slopes themselves need to be modeled in order to code the interaction.
For the example in the book, say we have a linear model $$\mu_i = \alpha + \lambda_{W,i} W_i + \beta_S S_i$$ where $$\lambda_{W,i} = \beta_W + \beta_{WS} S_i$$ is the model encoding the interaction between shade and water.</description></item><item><title>Choosing Prediction Over Explanation in Psychology</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/Choosing-Prediction-Over-Explanation-in-Psychology/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/Choosing-Prediction-Over-Explanation-in-Psychology/</guid><description>Abstract:
Psychology has historically been concerned, first and foremost, with explaining the causal mechanisms that give rise to behavior. Randomized, tightly controlled experiments are enshrined as the gold standard of psychological research, and there are endless investigations of the various mediating and moderating variables that govern various behaviors. We argue that psychology’s near-total focus on explaining the causes of behavior has led much of the field to be populated by research programs that provide intricate theories of psychological mechanism but that have little (or unknown) ability to predict future behaviors with any appreciable accuracy.</description></item><item><title>circadian rhythm</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/health/circadian-rhythm/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/health/circadian-rhythm/</guid><description/></item><item><title>climate change solutions</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/climate-change-solutions/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/climate-change-solutions/</guid><description>measuring impact greenhouse gases are measured in units of ==tons== or parts per million (PPM), which is the fraction of the emitted gas as part of the whole atmosphere.
Average American ==19 tons== of GHG emissions per year. (breakdown?)
It takes about 15 Gigatons of CO2 to raise the atmospheric concentration by 1ppm. We raise it about 2.5 ppm per year. (~35 gigatons of CO2 produced annually)
Megaton = 1 million t¸ZZvbons.</description></item><item><title>cohens D</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/cohens-d/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/cohens-d/</guid><description/></item><item><title>collective dynamics of small-world networks</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/Collective-dynamics-of-small-world-networks/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/Collective-dynamics-of-small-world-networks/</guid><description>A key finding in network science , Watts and Strogatz discovered that small world networks are networks that have the property of having small average distance between nodes, while retaining high cliqueishness. They are somewhere between a fully random chaotic network, and a general one with no randomness (i.e. nodes are only connected via neighboring nodes).
This small-world effect (low average distance between nodes, high cliqueishness) emerges as a property of long-distance connections between a small number of nodes in a system (I know someone in California who works in law who knows someone connected to Obama).</description></item><item><title>collider bias</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/collider-bias/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/collider-bias/</guid><description>Given a Directed Acyclic Graph T -&amp;gt; S &amp;lt;- N, S is a collider since conditioning on it would create a statistical (but not necessarily causal) association between T and N. What this means is that once you learn or know about S (you condition on S by including it in the model), then learning about T also provides information about N.
Including colliders in models can introduce unwanted statistical associations such as selection distortion effect s.</description></item><item><title>Collinearity isn't une maladie that needs curing</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/Collinearity-isnt-une-maladie-that-needs-curing/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/Collinearity-isnt-une-maladie-that-needs-curing/</guid><description>Source .
Read this article when doing linear regression and are dealing with potential multicollinearity .
Every now and again, some worried student or collaborator asks me whether they’re “allowed” to fit a regression model in which some of the predictors are fairly strongly correlated with one another. Happily, most Swiss cantons have a laissez-faire policy with regard to fitting modelsmodèles with correlated predictors, so the answer to this question is “yes”.</description></item><item><title>commitment</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/commitment/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/commitment/</guid><description>Via Sasha, 2020-12-25: Phil by doing research you will get a good job. if you do easy random jobs like teaching English you are losing time. You need to get material stability as priority. Then you will see your creative powers can blossom. These few years I suggest you to focus on down to earth career. So you have food and means to travel. And also it will teach you a lot.</description></item><item><title>common statistical tests are linear models</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/Common-statistical-tests/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/Common-statistical-tests/</guid><description>source linear regression models and independent t-test use: when two means predict a response variable, i.e.
$$y_i = \beta_0 + \beta_1{x_i},$$. The associated hypothesis test assumes for the null that $$H_0: \beta_1 = 0$$
ranked version (Mann-Whitney): same deal, except you rank/order $x$ and $y$:
$$rank(y_i) = \beta_0 + \beta_1{x_i},$$ $$H_0: \beta_1 = 0$$
Essentially, a hypothesis test on the slope is asking whether or not the slope is 0.</description></item><item><title>community detection algorithms</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/community-detection-algorithms/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/community-detection-algorithms/</guid><description>Some network science methods
nice video on Modularity sum of observed links ($\frac{l_s}{L}$) minus expected links ($(\frac{d_s}{2L})^2$) for each partition (predetermined) of a network. optimize for maximum modularity (i.e. repartition and repeat procedure of finding the ratio between observed and expected links) nice video on Girvan-Newman find shortest path for each node to every other node calculate edge weights repeat for every node sum up all the edge weights associated between every possible pair of nodes in the network get rid of edges with highest weight (i.</description></item><item><title>compassion</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/compassion/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/compassion/</guid><description>A large part of compassion is about perspective and tolerance. Perspective invites compassion by recognizing the context surrounding people. Age is a prime example. Older folks are often seen as abrasive, blunt, and downright rude. Unaware of the times, lacking perspective. While this is sometimes the case, there&amp;rsquo;s reason to give them the benefit of the doubt. For one it&amp;rsquo;s likely that their mental and physical faculties are in decline, which isn&amp;rsquo;t an excuse, but it is a truth that can lead us to simply laugh and brush off the offputting interactions you have with them.</description></item><item><title>complex systems</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/complex-systems/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/complex-systems/</guid><description>The world is a complex place. Complex systems is the study of that complexity.</description></item><item><title>confidence intervals</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/confidence-intervals/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/confidence-intervals/</guid><description>the theoretical long-run proportion of confidence intervals that contain the true value of the unknown parameter being estimated
R Psychologist: 95% confidence is a confidence that in the long-run 95 % of the CIs will include the population mean. It is a confidence in the algorithm and not a statement about a single CI.
In other words, 90% of confidence intervals computed at the 90% confidence level contain the parameter, 95% of confidence intervals computed at the 95% confidence level contain the parameter, 99% of confidence intervals computed at the 99% confidence level contain the parameter, etc.</description></item><item><title>confirmation bias</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/confirmation-bias/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/confirmation-bias/</guid><description/></item><item><title>confirmation bias</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/psychology/confirmation-bias/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/psychology/confirmation-bias/</guid><description>the phenomenon where we seek evidence that confirms our already existing beliefs</description></item><item><title>contextual memory</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/psychology/contextual-memory/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/psychology/contextual-memory/</guid><description/></item><item><title>conversation starts</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/relationships/conversation-starters/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/relationships/conversation-starters/</guid><description>See also 36-questions .
tags:: #dating #conversation What do you miss about being a kid? If someone gave you enough money to start a business – no strings attached – what kind of business would you want to start and why? Tell me about a relationship issue you’re having, and ask me for advice on how to fix it. If you could go back in time, what’s one piece of advice you’d give to your younger self?</description></item><item><title>Convolutional Neural Networks</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/Convolutional-NN/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/Convolutional-NN/</guid><description/></item><item><title>cooking recipes</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/health/cooking-recipes/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/health/cooking-recipes/</guid><description>Recipes to try and things I&amp;rsquo;ve made.
Tofu Spring Rolls</description></item><item><title>correlation</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/correlation/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/correlation/</guid><description>Correlation is standardized covariance : $$corr(x,y) = \frac{Cov(x,y)}{sd(x)sd(y)}$$. It provides a value between -1 and 1 that denotes the steepness of a slope and its direction (positive or negative) between two data variables.</description></item><item><title>covariance</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/covariance/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/covariance/</guid><description>#flashcards
Relation to variance variance alone cannot tell you about the relationship between two variables. Covariance, then, is a useful measure of how two variables relate, or covary, with each other.
Formally covariance is the expected product of two mean-centered variables:
$$Cov(X,Y) = E[(X-E(X))(Y-E(Y))]$$
It&amp;rsquo;s usually computed as:
$$Cov(X,Y) = \frac{1}{n-1}\sum_{i}{(x_i - \bar{x})}{(y_i - \bar{y})}$$
Some properties:
$$Cov(X,Y) = E(XY) - E(X)E(Y)$$
Relation to correlation Covariance gives direction of the relationship, but not strength.</description></item><item><title>cross validation</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/cross-validation/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/cross-validation/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Cross-Entropy</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/Cross-Entropy/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/Cross-Entropy/</guid><description>In the context of neural networks, the cross entropy function takes in the output of the softmax function along with the correct labels for each observation and calculates the cross entropy. The cross entropy is the entropy of correct-label distribution plus the KL-Divergence of the correct-label distribution and the predicted-label distribution.
Cross Entropy Loss on a training example $i$: $$L_{i} = \sum_j = -Y_{ij} log(q_j) = -\log(q_{l_i})$$
Since $Y_{ij}$ is a one hot encoded vector, the multiplication in the middle ends up to be the log term on the right, which is the negative log of $q_{l_i}$, or the softmax ($q$) of the correct label ($l_i$).</description></item><item><title>data ethics</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/Data-ethics/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/Data-ethics/</guid><description/></item><item><title>date ideas</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/relationships/date-ideas/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/relationships/date-ideas/</guid><description>See also 36 questions and conversation starters
ideas picnic and hike at Rock Point word poems - choose a word at random from a list and write a poem, essay, or piece about it slacklining biking to causeway Triple Buckets Swimming Hole (by Huntington Gorge) making food together (pizza)</description></item><item><title>David Whyte</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/Poems/David-Whyte/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/Poems/David-Whyte/</guid><description/></item><item><title>death</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/psychology/death/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/psychology/death/</guid><description> A course at Yale Robert S contemplations on his dying</description></item><item><title>decision trees</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/decision-tree/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/decision-tree/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Deep Learning</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/Deep-Learning/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/Deep-Learning/</guid><description>#flashcards
Uses Computer Vision Medical Imaging Satellite geoimaging Natural Language Processing How do machines learn? Key components
Objective function learning rule architecture initialization environment (the data supplied during learning) Model Performance sensitivity ::the proportion of true positives correctly identified over all positive cases ($$\frac{TP}{TP+FP}$$), aka the True Positive Rate = $P[(\hat{Y}(X)=1|H_1\text{ is true}]$, aka == statistical power ==. $1-TPR$ is the ==false positive rate==, also known as the == Type I error ==.</description></item><item><title>dementia</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/health/dementia/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/health/dementia/</guid><description/></item><item><title>depression</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/mental-health/depression/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/mental-health/depression/</guid><description/></item><item><title>diabetes</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/health/diabetes/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/health/diabetes/</guid><description/></item><item><title>diffusion-limited aggregation</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/diffusion-limited-aggregation/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/diffusion-limited-aggregation/</guid><description>references Form + Code Coding DLAs challenge Coding DLA and Frost in Python</description></item><item><title>directory</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ABCD/directory/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ABCD/directory/</guid><description>notes on the ABCD Study ABCD Project ABCD pre-registration Structural brain correlates of adolescent resilience</description></item><item><title>directory</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/health/directory/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/health/directory/</guid><description>notes on health (see also mental health ) caffeine sleep brain-derived neurotropic factor circadian rhythm meditation omega 3 fatty acids smoking The Ideal Day Andrew Huberman</description></item><item><title>directory</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/directory/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/directory/</guid><description>a directory of ideas backfire effect career climate change solutions Everything is fertile heartbreak Immanuel Kant confirmation bias How to Bike Across America Rooms Tiny Beautiful Things</description></item><item><title>directory</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/learning/directory/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/learning/directory/</guid><description>notes and articles on Learning anki Education at a Bat Learning memory spaced repetition</description></item><item><title>directory</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/neuro/directory/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/neuro/directory/</guid><description>Neuroscience notes amygdala BOLD signal x fmri dopamine Friston Free Energy Principle Modeling Group fMRI Data with Mixed Models network neuroscience</description></item><item><title>directory</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/psychology/directory/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/psychology/directory/</guid><description>notes on psychology A Life of One&amp;rsquo;s Own agendaless attention Happiness How to Feel Everything loneliness meaningness People-Watching psychological richness</description></item><item><title>directory</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/relationships/directory/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/relationships/directory/</guid><description>notes on relationships Am I Too Picky To Find Love An Instruction Manual to Oneself Be The Change You Want to See date ideas Maybe Friendship Should Be at the center of Life Love as a Way of Being Mating in Captivity Sex Statistics The Pleasures of Reading Together in Bed What Relationships Should Be About The School of Life</description></item><item><title>directory</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/directory/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/directory/</guid><description>notes on statistics distributions binomial distribution Exponential distribution Gaussian distribution Poisson distribution t-distribution tests Common statistical tests are linear models ANOVA Expectation power t-test t-statistic Type I error Type II error z-score models statistical independence linear regression logistic regression log-log regression maximum likelihood estimation mixed effects models variance covariance standard error standard deviation inference correlation multicollinearity effect size R-squared cohens-d confidence intervals Ecological Fallacy Simpson&amp;rsquo;s-Paradox information theory mutual information KL Divergence just cause causality causal inference Collinearity isn&amp;rsquo;t une maladie that needs curing collider bias post-treatment bias selection-distortion effect The Haunted DAG &amp;amp; The Causal Terror survivorship bias Bayesian The Bayesian New Statistics Bayes factor Bayesian Statistics Bayes all the way up Statistical Rethinking Highest Density Interval Monte Carlo methods markov chain monte carlo see also Machine Learning Deep Learning</description></item><item><title>dopamine</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/neuro/dopamine/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/neuro/dopamine/</guid><description/></item><item><title>dot product</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/dot-product/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/dot-product/</guid><description>An element-wise multiplication between two equal-sized vectors.
Proof of $a^Tb=||a|| ||b|| \cos{\theta}$ What we need to know is the law of cosines and the distributive property of two vectors:
law of cosines helps us find the length of a triangle given two other sides of a general triangle (meaning it&amp;rsquo;s not necessarily a right triangle). It states that $$c^2 = a^2 + b^2 - 2ab\cos{\theta}$$ distributive property for dot product: $$||a-b||^2 = (a-b)^T(a-b) = a^2 - 2a^Tb + b^2$$ So say we have a triangle with sides $a$, $b$, and $c$.</description></item><item><title>Early Diagnosis of Alzheimer's Disease with Deep Learning</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/neuro/Early-Diag-Alz-DL/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/neuro/Early-Diag-Alz-DL/</guid><description>Summary archiecture: stacked Autoencoders and softmax output layer classify: alzheimers disease and a possible precusor, Mild Cognitive Impairment dataset: ADNI database. 311 subjects (65 AD, 67 converters MCI, 102 non-converters MCI, 77 normal), gray matter volume (structural inputs) early diagnosis of AD is primarily associated with detection of Mild Cognitive Impairment Stacked Autoencoders can be seen as higher representations of the previous layer in that they encode the data into abstract features the proposed neural network does a better job of multiclassification than SVM</description></item><item><title>Ecological-Fallacy</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/Ecological-Fallacy/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/Ecological-Fallacy/</guid><description>Making individual-based claims (within) using group-level results (between)</description></item><item><title>Education at Bat</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/learning/Education-at-Bat/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/learning/Education-at-Bat/</guid><description>When Harvard Graduate School of Education Professor David Perkins looked back at his childhood little league and &amp;ldquo;backyard baseball&amp;rdquo; experiences, he found the perfect metaphor for the set of teaching concepts presented in his 2008 book, Making Learning Whole: How Seven Principles of Teaching Can Transform Education .
Asked in an interview with Usable Knowledge to describe how he would like educators to work with his ideas, Perkins says, “They should get a rough sense of the ideas and start using them….</description></item><item><title>effect size</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/effect-size/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/effect-size/</guid><description>definition a measure that determines the ==practical significance== of scientific results
An effect size is a standardized measurement that compares the size of some statistical effect to a reference quantity, such as the variability of the statistic.
why they&amp;rsquo;re useful They are a standardized metric (scale free) that enables comparison (e.g. meta analysis) and communication of results using effect sizes from prior studies is useful for planning new studies via statistical power by providing an indication of what sample size is necessary to observe a statistically significant result two families: D and r Effect sizes can be grouped in two families (Rosenthal, 1994): The d family (consisting of ==standardized mean differences==) and the r family (measures of ==strength of association==).</description></item><item><title>entropy</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/entropy/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/entropy/</guid><description>The average amount of information, surprise, or uncertainty associated with given a random variable&amp;rsquo;s possible outcomes.
$$H(X) = E[-log(P(X))] = -\sum_i^N p(x_i)log(p(x_i)) $$
If $log$ base $2$ is used, then the units are in bits and represent the minimum bits of information needed to encode the information associated with $X$.</description></item><item><title>Esther Perel</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/psychology/Esther-Perel/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/psychology/Esther-Perel/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Everything is Fertile</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/Everything-is-fertile/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/Everything-is-fertile/</guid><description>Tim Urban on “whoa” moments and living with aliveness:
Psychedelic methods aside, I’d say this:
The best way not to experience a:: ::whoa moment:: :: is to live your days exactly how you normally do. You know how when you brush your teeth, you can think about something totally different and it doesn’t affect your ability to brush? Because it’s all being done by your subconscious? Well living your normal routine day is kind of like that—your brain is mostly on autopilot, and you’re living largely in an unconscious and comfortable groove.</description></item><item><title>exercise</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/health/exercise/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/health/exercise/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Exponential Distribution</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/Exponential-Distribution/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/Exponential-Distribution/</guid><description>Probability density function: $$f(x,\lambda)={\lambda}e^{-\lambda{x}}$$ where $\lambda$ is the rate parameter.
Expectation: $$E[X] = \frac{1}{\lambda} $$ in words, if the rate of calls is 2 per hour, then you can expect to wait half an hour between every call. The expectation is the average displacement, or the inverse of the rate.
Variance: $$Var[X] = \frac{1}{\lambda^2} $$, so the standard deviation is equal to the mean.</description></item><item><title>fast ai</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/fastai/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/fastai/</guid><description>Lesson 1 Education at Bat : Some principles for learning
A professor in the Harvard school of education, David Perkins, recommends some principles for learning that work better for most people (in essence, play and practice first before theory):
Play the whole game Make the game worth playing Work hard on the hard parts (idea of deliberate practice)</description></item><item><title>Finland is the Happiest Country in the World, and the Finns Aren't Happy About It</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/psychology/finland-happy/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/psychology/finland-happy/</guid><description>Finland is the Happiest Country in the World, and the Finns Aren&amp;rsquo;t Happy About It Re: [[notes/psychology/Happiness]], I find this article ( Finland is the Happiest Country in the World, and the Finns Aren&amp;rsquo;t Happy About It ). The main point is that how you define happiness will change the rankings. Happiness in terms of ==average life satisfaction==, the Fins and other Scandanavian top the list. #flashcards
However, if it&amp;rsquo;s defined as daily experience of ==positive emotions==, Finland drops down the list while Latin American countries rise to the top.</description></item><item><title>friendship</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/relationships/friendship/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/relationships/friendship/</guid><description>David Whyte, on friendship Frindship is a mirror to presence and a testament to forgiveness. Friendship not only helps us see ourselves through another’s eyes, but can be sustained over the years only with someone who has repeatedly forgiven us for our trespasses as we must find it in ourselves to forgive them in turn. A friend knows our difficulties and shadows and remains in sight, a companion to our vulnerabilities more than our triumphs, when we are under the strange illusion we do not need them.</description></item><item><title>Friston Free Energy Principle</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/neuro/Friston-Free-Energy-Principle/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/neuro/Friston-Free-Energy-Principle/</guid><description>A Primer data comes in, we perceive it not all of it is useful for survival, we only want to pay attention to the stuff that causes this data tiger &amp;gt; mad? &amp;gt; bad smell &amp;gt; cookies ? &amp;gt; food micro random, macro stable - &amp;ldquo;attraction set&amp;rdquo; - we are a tightly-bounded pattern governed by dynamical systems
small subset of all possible ways to configure your atoms is You, your phenotype.</description></item><item><title>Galway Kinnell</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/Poems/Galway-Kinnell/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/Poems/Galway-Kinnell/</guid><description/></item><item><title>gaussian distribution</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/Gaussian-distribution/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/Gaussian-distribution/</guid><description>The PDF of the form: $$f(x) = \frac{1}{\sqrt{2{\pi}{\sigma^2}}}e^{-\frac{1}{2}(\frac{x-\mu}{\sigma})^2}$$
Expected mean: $$E[X] = \mu$$
Expected variance: $$E[(x-\mu)^2] = \sigma^2$$</description></item><item><title>general method of moments</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/general-method-moments/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/general-method-moments/</guid><description/></item><item><title>gradient descent</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/Gradient-Descent/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/Gradient-Descent/</guid><description>definition A method of optimizing parameters in a model so that we minimize the loss function. The key idea is to update our parameter values using the slope of the loss function.
To do this we define a &amp;ldquo;step&amp;rdquo;, which is a predefined learning rate times the slope/derivative/gradient of our loss function at a particular parameter value, and add it to that particular parameter value. This is akin to moving in the direction of the gradient until we reach the bottom of the loss function.</description></item><item><title>grapefruit</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/health/grapefruit/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/health/grapefruit/</guid><description>It&amp;rsquo;s known that grapefruit can delay the metabolism of certain drugs in the body and have other interaction effects, so much so that some drugs are required to have a label on them warning against their use with grapefruit.
Grapefruit (==200mL== of grapefruit juice, or a whole grapefruit) blocks the action of an enzyme in the small intestine called CYP3A4, which is an enzyme that helps metabolize many drugs. This can be a problem because the drugs stay longer in your bloodstream; they aren&amp;rsquo;t being broken down quickly enough.</description></item><item><title>gray matter</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/neuro/gray-matter/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/neuro/gray-matter/</guid><description>In contrast to white matter , which consists of long myelinated axons, gray matter consists of mostly cell bodies.</description></item><item><title>Hanging Out With My Brother</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/Hanging-Out-With-My-Brother/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/Hanging-Out-With-My-Brother/</guid><description>Link &amp;ldquo;Hell is other people, but life is other people if you care about them enough.&amp;rdquo;
The main character in red is shown chatting with his brother in blue about what&amp;rsquo;s bothering him. He has been working on a theory of the [[meaning of life]]. It describes the [[self]] as dependent on our relationship with others; it&amp;rsquo;s all connected. There&amp;rsquo;s a notion of distance in his diagram of these interconnected relationships, which he claims doesn&amp;rsquo;t matter as much as their quality.</description></item><item><title>Happiness</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/psychology/Happiness/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/psychology/Happiness/</guid><description>References How to be happy</description></item><item><title>health</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/health/health/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/health/health/</guid><description> burnout mental-health-index grapefruit and caffeine interaction smoking</description></item><item><title>heartbreak</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/heartbreak/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/heartbreak/</guid><description>David Whyte, on the inescapability and necessity of heartbreak Heartbreak is unpreventable; the natural outcome of caring for peoplegens and thingschoses over which we have no control, of holding in our affections those who inevitably move beyond our line of sight.
Heartbreak begins the moment we are asked to let go but cannot, in other words, it colors and inhabits and magnifies each and every day; heartbreak is not a visitation, but a path that human beings follow through even the most average life.</description></item><item><title>Highest Density Interval</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/Highest-Density-Interval/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/Highest-Density-Interval/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Horizon</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/Horizon/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/Horizon/</guid><description>quotes &amp;ldquo;It was important to Walsh that a human being, not a rover or a probe, first saw the bottom of the Pacific. &amp;ldquo;You can&amp;rsquo;t surprise a machine,&amp;rdquo; he said to me. And it is this capacity to appreciate the unknown, to be surprised by it, he believes, that will always set the human explorer apart from the machine. The moment of surprise informs you emphatically that the way you once imagined the world is not the way it is.</description></item><item><title>How Are You Difficult to Live With</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/relationships/How-Are-You-Difficult-to-Live-With/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/relationships/How-Are-You-Difficult-to-Live-With/</guid><description>How Are You Difficult to Live with? The idea that one is in many ways an extremely difficult person to be in a relationship with may sound rather improbable and even at points offensive. Yet fully understanding and readily and graciously admitting to this possibility might be the surest way of making sure one is an endurable proposition over the long-term. There are few people more deeply insufferable than those who don’t, at regular intervals, suspect they might be so.</description></item><item><title>How Do I Keep Myself from Sabotaging My Amazing New Relationship?</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/relationships/sabotage-relationship/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/relationships/sabotage-relationship/</guid><description>Dear Polly,
Like so many of us out there, I have been reading your column for years. Your book changed my life so much so that I now give copies of it out to friends. I am a very big fan.
For the first timetemps in a long time, I am in a good, healthy, happy relationship. My sparkly new boyfriend is remarkable. He treats me like I’m worth a million bucks.</description></item><item><title>How People Learn to Become Resilient</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/psychology/How-People-Learn-to-Become-Resilient/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/psychology/How-People-Learn-to-Become-Resilient/</guid><description>How People Learn to Become Resilient - Maria Konnikova Norman Garmezy, a developmental psychologist and clinician at the University of Minnesota, met thousands of children in his four decades of research. But one boy in particular stuck with him. He was nine years old, with an alcoholic mother and an absent father. Each day, he would arrive at school with the exact same sandwich: two slices of bread with nothing in between.</description></item><item><title>How to Be Happy</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/psychology/How-to-be-happy/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/psychology/How-to-be-happy/</guid><description>How to be happy Source: https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/ZbgCx2ntD5eu8Cno9/how-to-be-happy Synopsis: Some things you can do to be a happier person, backed by research
The correlates of Happiness Earlier , I noted that there is an abundance of research on factors that correlate with subjective well-being (individuals' own assessments of their happiness and life satisfaction).
Factors that don&amp;rsquo;t correlate much with happiness include: age,7 gender,8 parenthood,9 intelligence,10 physical attractiveness,11 and money12 (as long as you&amp;rsquo;re above the poverty line).</description></item><item><title>How to Bike Across America</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/How-to-Bike-Across-America/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/How-to-Bike-Across-America/</guid><description>National Geographic Travel photographer Tyler Metcalfe recently quit his job and sold off his possessions. Now he’s setting off on the American Bike Project—an epic solo adventure of cross-country cycling that will take him 4,228 miles across the United States.
Two years ago, National Geographic Digital Nomad Robert Reid wrote an article called “ Are Bikes the New Tour Bus? ” Robert argues that bikes are the best way to see a city, noting that biking is “more fun than public transit, quicker than walking, and cheaper than taxis or renting a car—not to mention better for the environment.</description></item><item><title>How to Feel Everything</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/psychology/How-to-Feel-Everything/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/psychology/How-to-Feel-Everything/</guid><description>For when everything seems like shit
Source I just reread an Ask Polly letter that feels like a map to the psychosocial snares of the 2010s. It’s all in there: Navigating childhood as a sensitive kid who’s blamed for everything bad that happens in the family, struggling through life as a young adult without knowing how to seek joy. And once happiness finally arrives, the LW feels so fearful she’ll lose it that she can’t even enjoy it.</description></item><item><title>Immanuel Kant</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/Immanuel-Kant/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/Immanuel-Kant/</guid><description>Kant was a moral absolutist, in the sense that he believed there to be a consistent, almost mathematical morality that was to be followed if one wanted to be a moral human being.
(However he made the distinction between doing things for moral reasons and for other non-moral reasons)
Hypothetical Imperatives If-then commands you should follow in order to satisfy some desire. Not exactly about morality.
Categorical Imperative You have to follow these imperatives, regardless of desires.</description></item><item><title>inferring mental health from smartphone data</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/psychology/inferring-mental-health-from-smartphone-data/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/psychology/inferring-mental-health-from-smartphone-data/</guid><description>Source: Psyche .
We use factors such as language, prior behavior, relationship quality, and socioeconomic status to predict mental health outcomes. these are all proxies&amp;hellip; imperfect, but useful in some cases. claim is that digital tools can help clinicians make decisions as to how to best serve their patients.
Feels Orwellian though, lack a imposition on one&amp;rsquo;s right to privacy. Maybe this is something worth signing that away for though, and could work well if the right safeguards are in place.</description></item><item><title>information theory</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/information-theory/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/information-theory/</guid><description>The mathematical theory of communication developed by Claude Shannon
What made it so impactful? Idea of channel limits $C_t = W\log_{2}\frac{P+N}{N}$. Every communication channel has a speed limit, measured in binary digits per second. Above the limit it is mathemtically impossible to send an error-free message (i.e. loss of information when you go above the channel speed limit).
But below the limit, it is always possible to transmit a message with zero error, regardless of noise or how weak the signal is.</description></item><item><title>k-means clustering</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/k-means-clustering/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/k-means-clustering/</guid><description/></item><item><title>k-nearest neighbors</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/K-nearest-neighbors/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/K-nearest-neighbors/</guid><description>a machine learning method that classifies data based on the k-points nearest to it.</description></item><item><title>KL Divergence</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/KL-Divergence/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/KL-Divergence/</guid><description>Intuition A tool to measure how different two probability distributions are.
The motivation is that we often want to model observed data using a simpler approximated distribution (Q) if we think that the data are generated by a complex, intractable distribution (P). KL Divergence measures how much information we expect to lose (in units of bits) under the approximated distribution (Q). $$D_{KL}(P||Q) = E_p[\log\frac{p(x)}{q(x)}]$$
Since we&amp;rsquo;re concerned with information loss, we first need a measure of information.</description></item><item><title>learning</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/learning/Learning/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/learning/Learning/</guid><description>The Myth of Learning Styles Source Learning “style” is task and domain specific, not learner specific. Variation in learning is better explained by interest and aptitude rather than leaning modality preference. – Nicole Barbaro
In order to study the effect of learning styles on learning, one needs an outcome measure. One obvious solution is to administer a test. Now we can setup an experiment (A randomized control trial).</description></item><item><title>linear algebra</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/linear-algebra/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/linear-algebra/</guid><description>Concepts dot product vector space system of linear equations</description></item><item><title>linear regression</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/linear-regression/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/linear-regression/</guid><description>#flashcards
Multiple Linear Regression The defining question of multiple linear regression is: What is the value of knowing each predictor, once we already know the other predictors? Implicit in this question are: (1) a focus on the value of the predictors for description of the sample, instead of forecasting a future sample; and (2) the assumption that the value of each predictor does not depend upon the values of the other predictors.</description></item><item><title>log log regression</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/log-log-regression/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/log-log-regression/</guid><description>sourced somewhere from Twitter
When using linear regression, when should you log-transform your data?
Many people seem to think that any non-Gaussian, continuous variables should be transformed so that the data “look more normal.” Linear regressionrégression does in fact assume the errorsles erreurs are normally distributed, but it is fairly robust to violations of this assumption, and there are no such assumptions regarding the predictor variables. What is often ignored or misunderstood is the impact that variable transformations have on the linearity assumption of regression models, and on coefficient interpretation.</description></item><item><title>Logistic Regression</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/logistic-regression/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/logistic-regression/</guid><description>Summary A statistical model that models the relationship between a binary dependent variable and a set of explanatory variables.
What the model finds is the probability that an observation belongs to one class or the other, given a set of independent variables.
That probability, say $p$, is being estimated by the coefficients in the estimated regression function $$\hat{p}=\frac{e^{z}}{1+e^{z}}=\sigma(z)$$ where $z$ is the linear combination of independent variables: $$z = \beta_0 + {\beta_1}{x_1} + {\beta_2}{x_2} + &amp;hellip; + {\beta_n}{x_n}$$ and $\sigma$ is the sigmoid function.</description></item><item><title>Loneliness</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/psychology/loneliness/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/psychology/loneliness/</guid><description>Books The Lonely City</description></item><item><title>loss function</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/loss-function/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/loss-function/</guid><description>a function in machine learning that indicates how &amp;lsquo;off&amp;rsquo; our model predictions are relative to the actual values</description></item><item><title>Louise Gluck</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/Poems/Louise-Gl%C3%BCck-1/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/Poems/Louise-Gl%C3%BCck-1/</guid><description>About Louise Glück The Crimson Poetry Foundation</description></item><item><title>Louise Gluck</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/Poems/Louise-Gl%C3%BCck/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/Poems/Louise-Gl%C3%BCck/</guid><description>About Louise Glück The Crimson Poetry Foundation poems Matins</description></item><item><title>Love</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/love/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/love/</guid><description/></item><item><title>markov chain monte carlo</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/markov-chain-monte-carlo/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/markov-chain-monte-carlo/</guid><description>A class of sampling algorithms based on Monte Carlo methods Idea: After a massive number of samples, the probability of different realizations of a random variable converge to the true probabilities
Metropolis-Hastings algorithm One example of MCMC. It&amp;rsquo;s a method of getting samples of parameter values from unknown posterior distributions.
Via wikipedia:
The algorithm can estimate any distribution P provided a function $f(x)$ that is proportional to P and the values of $f(x)$ can be calculated.</description></item><item><title>Mary Oliver</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/Poems/Mary-Oliver/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/Poems/Mary-Oliver/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Mating in Captivity</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/relationships/Mating-in-Captivity/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/relationships/Mating-in-Captivity/</guid><description>Chapter 1: Why The Quest for Security Saps Erotic Vitality marriage and passion weren&amp;rsquo;t always bound together it took the sexual revolution of the 60s, the breakthrough of birth control, and the advancement of women&amp;rsquo;s rights before people were able to more freely choose their partners and consider these higher level desires the tradeoff of this gained freedom and independence is tangled with an increasing sense of loneliness , which is then imposed upon our romantic relationships .</description></item><item><title>Matins</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/Poems/Matins/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/Poems/Matins/</guid><description>You want to know how I spend my time? I walk the front lawn, pretending to be weeding. You ought to know I&amp;rsquo;m never weeding, on my knees, pulling clumps of clover from the flower beds: in fact I&amp;rsquo;m looking for courage, for some evidence my life will change, though it takes forever, checking each clump for the symbolic leaf, and soon the summer is ending, already the leaves turning, always the sick trees going first, the dying turning brilliant yellow, while a few dark birds perform their curfew of music.</description></item><item><title>maximum likelihood estimation</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/maximum-likelihood-estimation/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/maximum-likelihood-estimation/</guid><description>What is a likelihood? How likely is it that we observe the data we have under a specific model, given a set of parameter values that define it. Maximizing the likelihood means choosing estimates of the parameters that produce a model that best matches our data.
Actually calculating the MLE involves calculating the likelihood for each case/observation under a specified model, and then taking the product of each likelihood together. E.</description></item><item><title>meaning</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/meaning/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/meaning/</guid><description/></item><item><title>meaningness</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/psychology/meaningness/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/psychology/meaningness/</guid><description>meaningness: the ambiguous quality of meaningfulness and meaninglessness that we encounter in practice. ==According to the stance that recognizes meaningness, meaning is real but not definite. It is neither objective nor subjective. It is neither given by an external force nor a human invention.==
six textures of meaningness and the complete stance
wonder curiosity humor play enjoyment creation meaning and meaninglessness
unity, diversity, separateness
purpose
self</description></item><item><title>meditation</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/mental-health/meditation/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/mental-health/meditation/</guid><description>mindfulness On sex and mindfulness So she stopped comparing her experience with her expectations and simply allowed her experience to be what it is. She just enjoyed the sex she was having instead of worrying about whether it was the sex she “should” be having. She created an environment of acceptance, where the parts of her mind that needed to worry, that needed to avoid something bad happening, could instead move toward something good.</description></item><item><title>memory</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/learning/memory/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/learning/memory/</guid><description>projects one photo a day: on how rituals affect memory</description></item><item><title>mental health</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/mental-health/mental-health/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/mental-health/mental-health/</guid><description>articles and notes on mental health a network theory of mental disorders inferring mental health from smartphone data Adverse Childhood Experiences depression psilocybin resilience The School of Life</description></item><item><title>Mental Health COVID-19 Teen Study in Iceland</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/mh-covid-teens/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/mh-covid-teens/</guid><description>Summary Background Adolescence represents a crucial developmental period in shaping mental health trajectories. In this study, we investigated the effect of the COVID-19 pandemic on mental health and substance use during this sensitive developmental stage.
Methods In this longitudinal, population-based study, surveys were administered to a nationwide sample of 13–18-yearolds in Iceland in October or February in 2016 and 2018, and in October, 2020 (during the COVID-19 pandemic).</description></item><item><title>Messenger</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/Poems/Messenger/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/Poems/Messenger/</guid><description>My work is loving the world.
Here the sunflowers, there the hummingbird —
equal seekers of sweetness.
Here the quickening yeast; there the blue plums.
Here the clam deep in the speckled sand.
Are my boots old? Is my coat torn?
Am I no longer young, and still not half-perfect? Let me
keep my mind on what matters,
which is my work,
which is mostly standing still and learning to be</description></item><item><title>method of moments</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/method-of-moments/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/method-of-moments/</guid><description>How they work Assume we have a population, and within that population there exist processes that generated it, and that we expect certain Expectation values. We don&amp;rsquo;t know those values, but the moment of methods says that we can estimate them using our sample.
This is best demonstrated with an example. Suppose we know that there exists some expectation operator such that $E[X]=\mu$ in the population of interest. We don&amp;rsquo;t know what $\mu$ is, but we can use our sample to estimate it.</description></item><item><title>mixed models</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/mixed-models/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/mixed-models/</guid><description>Models that involve using fixed AND random effects to estimate the effect of explanatory variables on an outcome variable.
But it depends on who you ask, according to Andrew Gelman:
Fixed effects are constant across individuals, and random effects vary. For example, in a growth study, a model with random intercepts 𝑎𝑖 and fixed slope 𝑏 corresponds to parallel lines for different individuals 𝑖, or the model $y_{it} = a_i + bt$.</description></item><item><title>modeling group fMRI data with mixed models</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/neuro/Modeling-Group-fMRI-Data-with-Mixed-Models/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/neuro/Modeling-Group-fMRI-Data-with-Mixed-Models/</guid><description>mixed models Motivation Often the effect of interest in research (say changes in political opinion after watching an advertisement, or the experimental condition of an fMRI study) is different depending on the group or level its a part of (e.g. across different universities, scanner, hospital, state, city).
Fixed effects are those that are sampled on all levels of an effect (i.e. you are accounting for all universities in your distribution when you calculate your effect.</description></item><item><title>Monte Carlo methods</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/Monte-Carlo-methods/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/Monte-Carlo-methods/</guid><description>via Probabilistic ML:
Algorithms that compute expectations by repeated random sampling, using samples $x_i$ ~ $p(x)$
Examples: $$\int f(x)p(x)dx \approx \frac{1}{S} \sum_{i=1}^S f(x_i)$$
$$\int p(x,y)dx \approx \sum_{i} p(y | x_i);$$
Caculating the ratio of a triangle&amp;rsquo;s area within a square. Sample a point. If it&amp;rsquo;s in the triangle, record that. Otherwise, it was part of the square.
Why is this useful? integrals are difficult
Monte Carlo works on every Integral</description></item><item><title>multicollinearity</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/multicollinearity/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/multicollinearity/</guid><description>Multicollinearity refers to two or more predictor variables that are correlated with each other.
What&amp;rsquo;s the problem with correlated predictors in linear regression ? It can be misleading.
The consequence of multicollinearity is that ==the posterior distribution will seem to suggest that none of the variables is reliably associated with the outcome, even if all of the variables are in reality strongly associated with the outcome.== This frustrating phenomenon arises from the details of how linear regression works.</description></item><item><title>mutual information</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/mutual-information/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/mutual-information/</guid><description>An information theory metric that evaluates how much two features (distributions) &amp;lsquo;depend&amp;rsquo; on each other. (see also KL-Divergence )
If knowing the value of one feature is highly predictive of the value of another feature, than those two features have high mutual information.
Conversely, if knowing the value of one feature does not help in predicting the other, they are likely to be reletively independent and unpredictive, and therefore share low mutual information.</description></item><item><title>Natural Language Processing</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/Natural-Language-Processing/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/Natural-Language-Processing/</guid><description>fastai One debate in the field of NLP, and Machine Learning in general using machine learning to predict outcomes but not necessarily understand the underlying phenomena; vs. a more theory-driven approach CNN - one way of incorporating hypotheses, structures, and prior knowledge into your model when modeling underlying mechanisms Some Preprocessing Lemmatization - fancier stemming More computationally expensive, slower than stemming, but more accurate Use lemmatization when you have less data, and you want to emphasize the importance of more significant words&amp;hellip; Might not want to remove stop words when you have lots of data and are using a large neural net to deal with more complexity Stemming - getting roots of words (simpler) by chopping ends off Factorization analogous to matrix decomposition think of multiplication tree, where the final factors of a number are prime similar with matrix decomposition, where the factor matrices have nice properties depending on the type of decomp Properties of matrices decomposed by SVD: $$ A = USV $$ $U$ is orthonormal - columns are orthogonal and pairwise-normalized (dot product between any two columns = 0, between itself = 1) $S$ is diagonal, and the values along the diagonal are essentially non-negative weights in descending order (principal components - the singular values!</description></item><item><title>network neuroscience</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/neuro/network-neuroscience/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/neuro/network-neuroscience/</guid><description>Abstract of famous Bassett paper Despite substantial recent progress, our understanding of the principles and mechanisms underlying complex brain function and cognition remains incomplete. Network neuroscience proposes to tackle these enduring challenges. Approaching brain structure and function from an explicitly integrative perspective, ==network neuroscience pursues new ways to map, record, analyze and model the elements and interactions of neurobiological systems.== Two parallel trends drive the approach: the availability of new empirical tools to create comprehensive maps and record ==dynamic patterns among molecules, neurons, brain areas and social systems==; and the theoretical framework and computational tools of modern network science.</description></item><item><title>network science</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/network-science/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/network-science/</guid><description>Networks are at the heart of complex systems Network science is the study of the structure and evolution of the networks underlying complex systems These networks are driven by a common set of fundamental laws and principles networks are comprised of nodes, which are linked to other nodes. If two nodes are linked to each other, than they are neighbors. The number of links a node has is the degree of the node Network Statistics Average degree: how connected is each node?</description></item><item><title>neural networks</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/neural-networks/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/neural-networks/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Nonreplicable publications are cited more than replicable ones</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/Nonreplicable-publications-are-cited-more-than-replicable-ones/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/Nonreplicable-publications-are-cited-more-than-replicable-ones/</guid><description>source Three influential replication projects ( 5 – 7 ) tried to systematically replicate the findings in top psychology, economics, and general science journals. In psychology, only 39% of the experiments yielded significant findings in the replication study, compared to 97% of the original experiments. In economics, 61% of 18 studies replicated, and among Nature/Science publications, 62% of 21 studies.
In addition, the relative effecteffect sizes of findings that did replicate were only 75% of the original ones.</description></item><item><title>Notes on Statistical Confounding</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/statistical-confounding/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/statistical-confounding/</guid><description>#flashcards
notes from a paper by Jacob Westfall on statistical confounding issues
Scientists study and want to make claims (inference) about the relationship between things (e.g. academic performance and household income). To do this they construct measures (variables) that quantify the phenomenon they want to understand. If a measure is significantly related to the outcome (statistically speaking), then it is inferred there is some sort of non-trivial relationship between the outcome and the process that the measure represents.</description></item><item><title>Null Hypothesis Significance Testing</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/Null-Hypothesis-Significance-Testing/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/Null-Hypothesis-Significance-Testing/</guid><description>Given that the null hypothesis is true, how unlikely is the data? $$p(Data|H_0 = \text{True})$$
If the likelihood of the data is unlikely (judged by a decision threshold: the p-value ), given that the null hypothesis is true, then we can reject the null hypothesis in favor of the alternative hypothesis The steps of NHST Formulate a hypothesis that embodies our prediction (without seeing the data) Specify the null and alternative hypotheses Collect data relevant to the hypothesis Fit a model to the data that represents the alternative hypothesis and compute a test statistic Compute the probability of observing the value of that test statistic assuming null hypothesis is true Assess the &amp;ldquo;statistical significance&amp;rdquo; of that result Common tests For comparing group mean differences: t-statistic and t-test</description></item><item><title>obesity</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/health/obesity/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/health/obesity/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Odds</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/Odds/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/Odds/</guid><description>The odds of an event is the ratio of the probability that the event occurs over the probability that the event doesn&amp;rsquo;t occur. e.g. $$odds(X)=\frac{P(X)}{1-P(X)}$$.
The odds ratio is a ratio of two odds. i.e. $$\frac{odds(X)}{odds(Y)}=\frac{\frac{P(X)}{1-P(X)}}{\frac{P(Y)}{1-P(Y)}}$$ If we have a loaded coin where $P(heads_{loaded})=0.7$ and a regular coin where $P(heads)=0.5$, then the odds of getting heads on the loaded coin are $$\frac{odds(heads_{loaded})}{odds(heads)}=\frac{\frac{0.7}{0.3}}{\frac{0.5}{0.5}}=2.333$$.
So the odds of seeing heads on a loaded coin are 2.</description></item><item><title>omega 3 fatty acids</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/health/omega-3-fatty-acids/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/health/omega-3-fatty-acids/</guid><description>Three kinds:
ALA flaxseed oil, walnuts cannot be synthesized metabollically and must be directly obtained from diet EPA fish fish oil DHA fish fish oil</description></item><item><title>optimism</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/optimism/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/optimism/</guid><description/></item><item><title>p-value</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/p-value/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/p-value/</guid><description>#flashcards
p-value: the probability of observing a difference between the ==statistic== of two groups, when there is no true difference at all (false positive), over many rounds of observations (experiments, resamples, etc).
What this requires is that you calculate a test statistic that summarizes and compares two groups together. The p-value is the probability that you observe that test statistic under the null hypothesis.
The alpha/cutoff value is your tolerance level for ==false positives==, or Type-I-error .</description></item><item><title>People Watching</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/psychology/People-Watching/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/psychology/People-Watching/</guid><description>One of the best web series.
Hanging Out With My Brother</description></item><item><title>physical health</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/health/physical-health/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/health/physical-health/</guid><description/></item><item><title>poems</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/Poems/Poems-directory/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/Poems/Poems-directory/</guid><description>from How to Read and Why:
There is a shock of recognition when we read Walt Whitman at his strongest. Poetry, at the best, does us a kind of violence that prose fiction rarely attempts or accomplishes. The Romantics understood this as the proper work of poetry; to startle us out of our sleep-of-death into a more capacious sense of life. There is no better motive for reading and rereading the best of our poetry.</description></item><item><title>Poisson Distribution</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/Poisson-Distribution/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/Poisson-Distribution/</guid><description>#flashcards Great source: The Poisson Distribution and Poisson Process Explained
When to use it When you want to model the discrete counts of a process where the average time between events is known, but the exact timing of events is random.
When you want to find the probability of observing a particular number of events in a time period or the probability of some waiting time until the next event</description></item><item><title>post-treatment bias</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/post-treatment-bias/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/post-treatment-bias/</guid><description>The inclusion of a predictor that may confound treatment effects because it is the consequence of another predictor (e.g. using political interest instead of, say, socioeconomic status in a problem where the latter includes political party). This may bias an estimation of some intervention, as in the civic engagement treatment program below.
It is much less routine to worry about mistaken inferences arising from including variables that are consequences of other variables.</description></item><item><title>principal component analysis</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/principal-component-analysis/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/principal-component-analysis/</guid><description>In essence A method for summarizing data and reducing dimensionality an good intuitive explanation, via StatExchange : Imagine a big family dinner, where everybody starts asking you about PCA. First you explain it to your great-grandmother; then to you grandmother; then to your mother; then to your spouse; finally, to your daughter (who is a mathematician). Each time the next person is less of a layman. Here is how the conversation might go.</description></item><item><title>psilocybin</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/mental-health/psilocybin/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/mental-health/psilocybin/</guid><description>Peter Attia on the question of how to administer this drug at scale Part of the difficulty involves the subjective and personal experience of the trip. Set and setting are important. Should medical practitioners who prescribe these drugs have personal experience? I can imagine that there are some people who just won&amp;rsquo;t, and if prior experience is necessary, we may be doing a disservice to those who would otherwise be helped with the use of these compounds, at least at scale.</description></item><item><title>psychological richness</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/psychology/psychological-richness/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/psychology/psychological-richness/</guid><description>I recently read a Twitter thread from professor Erin Westgate on the concept of psychological richness. Traditionally we think of the good life in terms of either meaning or Happiness (historically eudaimonia and hedonism, respectively), though psychological richness is a distinct factor that is worth thinking about.
Psychologically rich lives, we argue, not only feel different from happy or meaningful lives. They are ==psychometrically distinct==, with different causes and different long-term outcomes, and can be assessed (both in the moment, and more globally) with different measures.</description></item><item><title>Psychology</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/psychology/Psychology/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/psychology/Psychology/</guid><description/></item><item><title>PTSD</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/mental-health/PTSD/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/mental-health/PTSD/</guid><description/></item><item><title>purpose</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/purpose/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/purpose/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Quartz Documentation</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/moc/directory/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/moc/directory/</guid><description>Setup Welcome to Quartz! Whether you&amp;rsquo;re setting up a website and project for the first time or a seasoned digital gardener, I hope that you&amp;rsquo;ll find something useful about this project.
Let&amp;rsquo;s get to business and get you started!
📚 Setup your own digital garden using Quartz 🔗 Linking with an Obsidian Vault 🎨 Customizing and Styling Quartz 🌍 Hosting Quartz online! Not convinced yet?</description></item><item><title>R-Squared</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/R-squared/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/R-squared/</guid><description>The proportion of the variance in the dependent variable (Y) predicted by the independent variable(s).
Formula: $$ 1 - \frac{SS_\text{residuals}}{SS_\text{total}}$$
where $${SS_\text{total}} = \sum_i({y_i - \bar{y}})^2$$ is the total sum of squares, and $${SS_\text{residuals}} = \sum_i(y_i - f_i)^2$$ where $f_i$ is the associated predicted value with index $i$.
Relevant when considering effect size</description></item><item><title>Random effects</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/Random-effects/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/Random-effects/</guid><description/></item><item><title>random-forests</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/random-forests/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/random-forests/</guid><description/></item><item><title>reading</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/reading/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/reading/</guid><description>how to read more books - find sufficient motivation (relevant for setting goals too; ask yourself why you want to do this, why you want to change) - intrinsic vs extrinsic</description></item><item><title>Reading Scientific Papers</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/Reading-Scientific-Papers/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/Reading-Scientific-Papers/</guid><description>I don&amp;rsquo;t remember the source but these are excellent guidelines
A big part of the challenge of reading papers is deciding which ones to read. There are a lot of papers out there, and only a few will be relevant to you. Therefore, deciding what to read is a nontrivial skill in itself. Research papers are the most useful when you have a specific problem or question in mind.</description></item><item><title>Recurrent Neural Networks</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/RNN/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/RNN/</guid><description/></item><item><title>relationships</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/relationships/relationships/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/relationships/relationships/</guid><description/></item><item><title>resilience</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/gratitude/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/gratitude/</guid><description/></item><item><title>resilience</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/mental-health/resilience/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/mental-health/resilience/</guid><description>What is resilience? An overview: How People Learn to Become Resilient How have people studied it? Ordinary Magic: Resilience Processes in Development Ann Masten: What is meant by &amp;lsquo;ordinary magic&amp;rsquo;? Early understanding of resilience implied it was a remarkable capability possessed by outlier children - i.e. invulnerable, invincible but research reveals it is more ordinary than depicted – &amp;ldquo;a common phenomenon that results in most cases from the operation of basic human adaptational systems.</description></item><item><title>resilience project</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/mental-health/resilience-project/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/mental-health/resilience-project/</guid><description>questions are there structural differences between high and low resilience kids? what about function? prior regions of interest: prefrontal cortex, amygdala, hippocampus connectivity differences? notes contextual memory are memories formed within a specific context. this is relevant to PTSD because traumatic events are deeply encoded in the mind and body. The process of recontextualizing, healing, reconnecting with yourself involves in part extinguishing these memories Nick found a non-linear interaction via a genetic programming approach between adversity and ventromedial prefrontal cortex volume divided by hippocampus volume methods feed network features (structural, functional) to machine learning model measures outcome: competence: Structural brain correlates of adolescent resilience adversity: Structural brain correlates of adolescent resilience ABCD Measures ABCD Youth 10 Item Delinquency Scale abcd_y10ids01 Behaviors that violate laws and social norms ABCD Youth Brief Problem Monitor - abcd_bpm01 Normed multi-informant monitoring of children&amp;rsquo;s functioning, youth report</description></item><item><title>rooms</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/Rooms/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/Rooms/</guid><description>Rooms, Abodes, Flats, Apartments
What it&amp;rsquo;s like to step into another person&amp;rsquo;s room. It&amp;rsquo;s the most intimate space of our lives, it&amp;rsquo;s our home and our mess, our shelter and our it&amp;rsquo;s ours. What are we doing when we invite someone in, to what are we inviting them to? A portal into our lives. It is a way of seeing who someone without necessarily engaging with them. When we meet and converse with someone, when we get to know them, we usually only give elevator pitches and summaries.</description></item><item><title>sauna</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/health/sauna/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/health/sauna/</guid><description>summary benefits (typically involving ~175F for ~20mins) dose-dependent reduction in rates of heart-disease and premature mortality less risk of developing dementia lower risk of psychosis (and possibly other mental health issues) highlights Much of the findings of late interest seem to result from a large population-based cohort study (Kuopio Ischemic Heart Disease Risk Factor (KIHD) Study) of health outcomes in 2300+ middle-aged men from Eastern Finland.</description></item><item><title>schizophrenia</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/mental-health/schizophrenia/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/mental-health/schizophrenia/</guid><description/></item><item><title>school of life</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/mental-health/school-of-life/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/mental-health/school-of-life/</guid><description>relationships What Relationships Should Be About How Are You Difficult to Live With Why We Go Cold On Our Partners An Instruction Manual to Oneself The Terrors of Being Loved Be The Change You Want to See Taking the Pressure off Love A-Pledge-for-Lovers The Pleasures of Reading Together in Bed</description></item><item><title>selection-distortion effect</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/selection-distortion-effect/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/selection-distortion-effect/</guid><description>source: In Statistical Rethinking , the author presents a particularly relevant example of how negative correlations arise from selection processes:
It seems like the most newsworthy scientific studies are the least trustworthy.
There&amp;rsquo;s no real underlying reason to believe that trustworthiness correlates with newsworthyness. But this spurious correlation can arise as a result of strict selection processes, such as selecting who gets science funding:
&amp;hellip; all that is necessary for such a negative correlation to arise is that peer reviewers care about both newsworthiness and trustworthiness.</description></item><item><title>sensitivity</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/sensitivity/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/sensitivity/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Sex Statistics</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/relationships/Sex-Statistics/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/relationships/Sex-Statistics/</guid><description>Sex Statistics How often do couples have sex?
I imagine that the frequency depending on many things:
individual levels of hornyness length of the relationship quality of the relationship opinions about sex and what sex is e.g. does oral sex count as sex? Or does it have to involve intercourse to be counted? What about things like gay sex vs. straight sex? via C: “When two lesbians have sex, it&amp;rsquo;s sex, but if a straight couple were to do the same thing, it&amp;rsquo;s not always considered sex?</description></item><item><title>Showcase</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/moc/showcase/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/moc/showcase/</guid><description>Want to see what Quartz can do? Here are some cool community gardens :)
Quartz Documentation (this site!) Strengthening Online Social Bonds: Research Garden Jacky Zhao&amp;rsquo;s Garden Anson Yu&amp;rsquo;s Garden Shihyu&amp;rsquo;s PKM Chloe&amp;rsquo;s Garden If you want to see your own on here, submit a Pull Request adding yourself to this file !</description></item><item><title>Simpson's Paradox</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/Simpsons-Paradox/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/Simpsons-Paradox/</guid><description>#flashcards
Simpson&amp;rsquo;s Paradox When the effects of aggregated data overshadow or drive away what may otherwise be significant effects when you ==partition the data into groups==.
example: UC Berekley study looking at admission bias between men and women. Aggregated data show it was biased against women, while partitioned data revealed that it favored women slightly (6 out of 85 departments biased against men; 4 biased against women).
The researchers concluded that women applied to more competitive departments with low rates of admission while men did the opposite.</description></item><item><title>simulation course</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/Simulation-Course/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/Simulation-Course/</guid><description>Lecture 1 Why Simulate? insight into analysis plan Anticipate what your data looks like statistical power analysis best way to understand p-values and p-hacking replicate effects of other studies and do statistics to verify results Basic Idea things we measure have an effect of interest plus random noise how much of that is noise, and how much is an effect? And if there is an effect, how big is it?</description></item><item><title>singular value decomposition</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/singular-value-decomposition/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/singular-value-decomposition/</guid><description/></item><item><title>sleep</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/health/sleep/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/health/sleep/</guid><description>#flashcards
melatonin What is melatonin?::it is a hormone produced in the pineal gland (brain) that helps regulate the circadian rhythm and the transition to sleep.
What regulates its release?::Light causes its production to stop, darkness to start.
Does exogenous melatonin improve sleep for adults? ? It can with adults who have issues related to Delayed Sleep-Wake Disorder and jet lag by realigning their circadian rhythm . But the evidence is mixed with otherwise healthy adults who have trouble falling and staying asleep.</description></item><item><title>smoking</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/health/smoking/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/health/smoking/</guid><description>It&amp;rsquo;s estimated that around 8 million people die prematurely from smoking.
It&amp;rsquo;s not the smoking itself but the effect it has on your heart and lungs.
The life expectancy of those who smoke regularly is around 10 years lower than that of non-smokers.
Historically smoking was one of those issues that no one believed was a problem until revealed by statistical analysis that it was. (The same thing happened regarding basic hand hygiene and maternal mortality following child birth.</description></item><item><title>social media</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/psychology/social-media/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/psychology/social-media/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Social Network Analysis</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/Social-Network-Analysis/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/Social-Network-Analysis/</guid><description>meta:: link Dr. Bernie Hogan Intro to Social Network Analysis (sociologists) Different from Network Science (physicists) How to link microlevel behaviors to macroscopic phenomenon (different scales; people to culture; citizens to institutions) view social structure on many levels global: facebook connections between countries, visualized as world map local: personal network types of questions: descriptive how polarized is a voting network how different is what i&amp;rsquo;m reading different from what another person in a different network is reading?</description></item><item><title>softmax</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/softmax/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/softmax/</guid><description>Given a range of values, softmax exponentiates each value and divides each one by the sum of the range of the exponentiated values, resulting in a probability distribution.
The softmax function is usually used in neural networks to turn neural network classification predictions into a probability distribution.</description></item><item><title>spaced repetition</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/learning/spaced-repetition/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/learning/spaced-repetition/</guid><description>spaced repetition systems make memory a choice. –Michael Nielson
what exactly do i want to remember?
&amp;lsquo;improved recall translates to improved understanding and general problem-solving&amp;rsquo;
you have more tools/information at your disposal. particularly with knowledge work, the ideas are easier to retrieve, which can lead to a creative breakthrough
the act of memory retrieval builds better memories than reminding
How to write good prompts: using spaced repetition to create understanding writing good prompts for articles and information:</description></item><item><title>specificity</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/specificity/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/specificity/</guid><description/></item><item><title>standard deviation</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/standard-deviation/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/standard-deviation/</guid><description>How far each observation &amp;lsquo;deviates&amp;rsquo; from the mean of the group. The standard deviation of a vector of values $x$ is:
$$SD_x = \sqrt{\frac{1}{n-1}\sum_i {(x_i - \bar{x})^2}} = \sqrt{Var(X)}$$
The $\frac{1}{n-1}$ term is the Bessel correction for bias in the estimation of the population variance
To get the sample variance , you can square $SD$</description></item><item><title>standard error</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/standard-error/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/standard-error/</guid><description>definition an estimate of uncertainty regarding the population parameter under interest (e.g. weight, height of adults in US) formula: $$\sqrt{\frac{SD_1^2}{n_1} + \frac{SD_2^2}{n_2}}$$ where $SD_1^2$ and $SD_2^2$ are the variances of each group relevance we&amp;rsquo;re uncertain about our parameters because we usually use a sample to estimate them. Standard error refers to the uncertainty surrounding the estimates of our parameters We can reduce the standard error by ==increasing our sample size== before calculating an estimate in other words, our standard error decreases as sample size increases Case in point: if we somehow the sample size reaches the population size, then we have 0 uncertainty about the parameter of interest</description></item><item><title>statistical independence</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/statistical-independence/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/statistical-independence/</guid><description>Two events, A and B, are statistically independent when $$ P(A|B) = P(A) $$
Quick example: the probability of drawing an ace with and without replacement.
With replacement: the probability of drawing an ace on the second draw after drawing an ace on the first draw is independent (because we replace the card).
Without replacement: we don&amp;rsquo;t replace the ace we draw the first time, so the probability of drawing another ace isn&amp;rsquo;t independent</description></item><item><title>statistical power</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/statistical-power/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/statistical-power/</guid><description>definition: the likelihood of finding a positive a result (1 - type II error; 1 - probability of false negative), given that it exists ($1-B$) or, via lakens-effect-size, the probability of correctly rejecting the null hypothesis. context for statistical power via Josh Starmer If we have two distributions of a particular variable (such as weight), and the difference between the means of the distributions is very large such that the p-value is very small, while also assuming that there is no weight difference at all (the null hypothesis is assumed to be true), we will be correct most of the time in rejecting the null hypothesis; it would be unlikely that the data points would come from the same distribution (meaning there may be something worth paying attention to that is causing two distrubtions to emerge, such as some sort of dietary intervention) However, in some cases, even though the data you obtain may be truly from two different distributions, you may get a p-value that suggests we cannot reject the null hypothesis.</description></item><item><title>statistical rethinking</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/Statistical-Rethinking/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/Statistical-Rethinking/</guid><description> Chapter-7-Statistical-Rethinking Chapter-8-Statistical-Rethinking</description></item><item><title>structural brain correlates of adolescent resilience</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ABCD/Structural-brain-correlates-of-adolescent-resilience/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ABCD/Structural-brain-correlates-of-adolescent-resilience/</guid><description>resilience : high competence despite history of high adversity The aim of the current study was to test for brain regions (structural) uniquely associated with positive functioning in the context of adversity, using detailed phenotypic classification.
model: brain structure ~ resilience Thus, the primary goal of the present project was to determine whether structural brain differences would be observed when adolescents who have experienced adversity yet are doing well in life were compared with both youth not at risk and youth not doing well, utilizing a large-scale sample with a range of experienced adversity and competence.</description></item><item><title>supervised learning algorithm</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/Supervised-Learning-algorithms/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/Supervised-Learning-algorithms/</guid><description> linear-regression logistic-regression support vector machines decision trees random-forests neural networks</description></item><item><title>support-vector-machines</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/support-vector-machines/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/support-vector-machines/</guid><description/></item><item><title>survivorship bias</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/survivorship-bias/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/survivorship-bias/</guid><description>A form of selection bias where what we see is the end result of things that &amp;ldquo;survived&amp;rdquo; some process, where others did not, thus leading us to false conclusions about the phenomena
examples thinking that an incident was not as dangerous as it was because everyone communicated with afterwards survived. Even if one knew that some people are dead, they would not have their voice to add to the conversation, leading to bias in the conversation.</description></item><item><title>system of linear equations</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/system-of-linear-equations/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/system-of-linear-equations/</guid><description>Generally of the form $$Ax = b$$ where $A$ represents a matrix of coefficients, $x$ is a vector of unknowns, and $b$ is a vector of known values. We usually want to solve for $x$, meaning we want to find a unique vector (if possible) that satisfies the equation.
In systems of linear equations, trying to solve for $x$ results in:
no solution a unique solution infinitely many solutions (redundancy) Geometrically, the solution to a system of linear equations is the point, line, plane, or hyperplane where each equation intersects.</description></item><item><title>t distribution</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/t-distribution/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/t-distribution/</guid><description>A distribution whose shape depends on number of degrees of freedom (higher df -&amp;gt; more like Gaussian distribution )</description></item><item><title>t statistic</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/t-statistic/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/t-statistic/</guid><description>#flashcards
$$t = \frac{\bar{X_1} - \bar{X_2}}{\sqrt{\frac{S_1^2}{n_1} + \frac{S_2^2}{n_2}}}$$ where the numerator is the difference in group means and the bottom is the square root of the standard error .
Another way of looking at the t-statistic is the ratio of explained variation to unexplained variation. In fMRI, this might be the average signal of the voxel under condition A minus the average signal of the voxel activated under condition B, divided by some measure of the noise.</description></item><item><title>t-test</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/t-test/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/t-test/</guid><description>Main question the t-test answers: What is the likelihood that we would find a t-statistic of this size, if the true difference between groups is zero or less (i.e. the directional null hypothesis)?
In other words, if we assume that the == t-distribution == captures our null hypothesis, how likely is it that we then observe our t-statistic ? If it&amp;rsquo;s unlikely then we can reject the null hypothesis. #flashcards</description></item><item><title>Taking the Pressure off Love</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/relationships/Taking-the-Pressure-off-Love/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/relationships/Taking-the-Pressure-off-Love/</guid><description>Taking the Pressure off Love It can feel very weird, and a bit threatening, to talk about taking the pressure off a relationship. Our collective, inherited Romantic culture likes to imagine functioning couples doing more or less everything together and being the centre of each other’s lives. The good couple is, we are told, one in which two peoplegens mean more or less everything to one another.
In a sound relationship, we are supposed to meet each other’s needs in every area of existence – from sex to intellectual stimulation, cooking styles to bedroom habits.</description></item><item><title>The Bayes New Stats</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/The-Bayesian-New-Statistics/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/The-Bayesian-New-Statistics/</guid><description>Abstract In the practice of data analysis, there is a conceptual distinction between Null Hypothesis Significance Testing , on the one hand, and estimation with quantified uncertainty on the other. Among frequentists in psychology, a shift of emphasis from hypothesis testing to estimation has been dubbed “the New Statistics” (Cumming 2014 ). A second conceptual distinction is between frequentist methods and Bayesian Statistics methods. Our main goal in this article is to explain how Bayesian methods achieve the goals of the New Statistics better than frequentist methods.</description></item><item><title>The God Who Loves You</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/Poems/The-God-Who-Loves-You/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/Poems/The-God-Who-Loves-You/</guid><description>By Carl Dennis It must be troubling for the god who loves you To ponder how much happier you’d be today Had you been able to glimpse your many futures.
It must be painful for him to watch you on Friday evenings Driving home from the office, content with your week—
Three fine houses sold to deserving families—
Knowing as he does exactly what would have happened Had you gone to your second choice for college, Knowing the roommate you’d have been allotted Whose ardent opinions on painting and music Would have kindled in you a lifelong passion.</description></item><item><title>The Green New Deal</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/The-Green-New-Deal/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/The-Green-New-Deal/</guid><description>Summary Introduced by Representative Alexandria Ocasio-Cortez of New York and Senator Edward J. Markey of Massachusetts, both Democrats, ==the proposal calls on the federal government to wean the United States from fossil fuels and curb planet-warming greenhouse gas emissions across the economy==. It also aims to ==guarantee new high-paying jobs in clean energy industries==.
Main provisions It says the entire world needs to get to net-zero emissions by 2050 (The Paris Agreement) — meaning as much carbon would have to be absorbed as released into the atmosphere — and the United States must take a “leading role” in achieving that.</description></item><item><title>The Haunted DAG and Causal Terror</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/The-Haunted-DAG-and-The-Causal-Terror/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/The-Haunted-DAG-and-The-Causal-Terror/</guid><description>Chapter 6 of Statistical Rethinking This chapter and the next are both about terrible things that can happen when we simply add variables to a regression, without a clear idea of a causal model. In this chapter, we’ll explore three different hazards: multicollinearity , post-treatment bias , and collider bias . We’ll end by tying all of these examples together in a framework that can tell us which variables we must and must not add to a model in order to arrive at valid inferences.</description></item><item><title>The Ideal Day via Andrew Huberman</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/health/The-Ideal-Day-Andrew-Huberman/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/health/The-Ideal-Day-Andrew-Huberman/</guid><description>#flashcards
Protocol 1: Record Your Daily Waking Time &amp;amp; Temperature Minimum Writing down when you wake up provides information about your temperature minimum Why is the temperature minimum important? It&amp;rsquo;s the time in each 24 hour cycle that your body temperature is lowest. Typically this is 2 hours before your wake up time. (E.G. Your lowest temperature is at 4am if you wake up at 6am, on average) Knowing this helps you shift your circadian clock (useful for travel, eating schedule) Protocol 2: Self-Generate Forward Motion (Outdoors) &amp;ldquo;Nerd speak for taking a walk&amp;rdquo;; &amp;ldquo;Forward ambulation&amp;rdquo; and generating optic flow lowers activity in the amygdala , which lowers levels of anxiety.</description></item><item><title>The Lives of Others</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/The-Lives-of-Others/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/The-Lives-of-Others/</guid><description>Last night I participated in a 3 hour online salon hosted by The Interintellect, a group of friendly internet patrons from all around the world who enjoy nerding out and talking about ideas. The topic last night was “The Immigrant Experience”, incredibly timely given the circumstances: what does it mean to be an immigrant? An expat? An émigré? We discussed open borders; finding vs. building a sense of home; identity as a shifting panorama shaped by one’s context; that unsettling feeling of in-betweenness as a spur for creativity and a sign of internal dialogue seeking resolution; beliefs and disillusion; immigrant optimism and the desire for a better life as buoys that have the strength to propel their lives and the country forward; our common humanity; redefining and striving toward American and Western ideals.</description></item><item><title>The Lonely City</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/psychology/The-Lonely-City/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/psychology/The-Lonely-City/</guid><description>A book by Olivia Laing in which she explores loneliness through art.</description></item><item><title>The Millennial Obsession with Starting Over</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/The-Millennial-Obsession-With-Starting-Over/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/The-Millennial-Obsession-With-Starting-Over/</guid><description>We pick up and move from city to city, trying on new identities but rarely sticking with them. It’s going to cost us.
The first time I moved, the first time I dove into the intoxicating lure of “new beginnings,” I brought few personal items with me to make my cinder-block-walled dorm room feel like home. No posters. No knickknacks to sit on our one window sill. No fairy lights. It looked like somewhere that could be wiped clean in minutes, whenever the next new beginning called, and no one would know I had been there.</description></item><item><title>The Pleasures of Reading Together in Bed</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/relationships/The-Pleasures-of-Reading-Together-in-Bed/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/relationships/The-Pleasures-of-Reading-Together-in-Bed/</guid><description>A nice article to come back to, on the simple joys of a long-term relationship. It may be my favorite thing to do.
A bedroom at around 9pm. It’s quiet, save for the rustle of the leaves in the garden outside.
We’re side by side, each absorbed in a different world. One of us might be in a submarine beneath the arctic ice floe, the other is flitting through the salons of 18th-century Paris.</description></item><item><title>The Power of Ritual - Turning Everyday Activities Into Soulful Practices</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/books/power-of-ritual/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/books/power-of-ritual/</guid><description>Much of the ideas in this book remind me of This Life by Martin Hägglund. What matters is this life. It is here that we relate and live and find meaning. The task is &amp;ldquo; To see a World in a Grain of Sand\And a Heaven in a Wild Flower &amp;rdquo;. Instead of finding salvation in some foreign abstract, we can build relationships with the people, nature, and world around us.</description></item><item><title>the replication crisis</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/replication-crisis/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/replication-crisis/</guid><description>sources Science Mag Nature Scott Maxwell Annual Reviews</description></item><item><title>The resilience paradox</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/mental-health/The-resilience-paradox/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/mental-health/The-resilience-paradox/</guid><description>Abstract Decades of research have consistently shown that the most common outcome following potential trauma is a ==stable trajectory of healthy functioning==, or resilience . However, attempts to predict resilience reveal a paradox: ==the correlates of resilient outcomes are generally so modest that it is not possible accurately identify who will be resilient to potential trauma and who not.==
That it&amp;rsquo;s not possible to identify who will be resilient vs those who aren&amp;rsquo;t is both expected and surprising.</description></item><item><title>The Terrors of Being Loved</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/relationships/The-Terrors-of-Being-Loved/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/relationships/The-Terrors-of-Being-Loved/</guid><description>The Terrors of Being Loved Ostensibly we all want love – but oddly, one of the hardest things to do is not to hold it against someone when they do actuallyréellement turn around and reciprocate our feelings.
It can be immensely hard not to feel that those who offer us love are in some way weak, mistaken, needy, craven or defective – and to be left a little queasy by their warmth, repulsed by their wish to hold us and to caress our necks; by their tender words and their capacity to find minor things about us endearing.</description></item><item><title>This-Life</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/books/This-Life/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/books/This-Life/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Tiny Beautiful Things</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/Tiny-Beautiful-Things/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/Tiny-Beautiful-Things/</guid><description>Dear Sugar,
I read your column religiously. I’m twenty-two. From what I can tell by your writing, you’re in your earlydébut forties. My question is short and sweet: What would you tell your twentysomething self if you could talk to her now?
Love, Seeking Wisdom
Dear Seeking Wisdom,
Stop worrying about whether you’re fat. You’re not fat. Or rather, you’re sometimes a little bit fat, but who gives a shit?</description></item><item><title>Tofu Spring Rolls</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/health/Tofu-Spring-Rolls/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/health/Tofu-Spring-Rolls/</guid><description>ingredients: Japanese sweet potatoes tofu marinated in soy sauce scallions carrots rice noodles rice paper rolls homemade peanut sauce soy sauce peanut butter honey lime pepper spinach</description></item><item><title>tropology</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/tropology/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/tropology/</guid><description>axes of meaning: power and peril(?)
what are stories?
brain as &amp;ldquo;story processor&amp;rdquo; via The Righteous Mind stories are about change (Gerald Prince 2009, Speech and Language Processing) three parts: a starting state (the beginning) events that move the story from the beginning to the end an ending state (the ending) purpose of stories?
efficient information processing via tropes/agreed upon meanings, culture ( Friston Free Energy Principle ?</description></item><item><title>TV tropes</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/TV-Tropes/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/TV-Tropes/</guid><description>What are tropes and why should we study and understand them?
We are storytelling/ meaning -making creatures that use various methods of abstraction (stories, metaphors, Poems , math) to represent and reason about our experiences and the world.
tropes are particular abstractions with generally agreed upon meanings used to convey and facilitate the communication of ideas within the structure of some larger/collective narrative, which itself can be viewed as a trope (the story of being human, the story of being a human with other humans, the story of being a citizen under US democracy – i.</description></item><item><title>Type I error</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/Type-I-error/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/Type-I-error/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Type II error</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/Type-II-error/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/Type-II-error/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Ultradian Cycles</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/health/Ultradian-Cycles/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/health/Ultradian-Cycles/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Ulysses' Compass - Ch 7 Statistical Rethinking</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/Chapter-7-Statistical-Rethinking/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/Chapter-7-Statistical-Rethinking/</guid><description>Ulysses' Compass A chapter about overfitting, underfitting, prediction models vs. causal mechanism models.
The problem with Parameters Adding more parameters to a model will usually improve prediction, despite the lacking causal associations. That&amp;rsquo;s because the model can retrodict the data to fit the model.
variance explained (by R-squared ):
$R^2 = \frac{var(outcome)-var(residuals)}{var(outcome)} = 1 - \frac{var(residuals)}{var(outcome)}$ $R^2$ increases even if we add random numbers as predictors that have no association to the outcome Entropy and Accuracy In navigating overfitting and underfitting, we must choose some measure of model performance.</description></item><item><title>unsupervised learning algorithms</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/unsupervised-learning-algorithms/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/unsupervised-learning-algorithms/</guid><description/></item><item><title>variance</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/variance/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/variance/</guid><description>Intuition $$Var(X) = {\frac{1}{n-1}\sum_i {(x_i - \bar{x})^2}} $$ How varied data points are around their ==mean==. #flashcards
Formal definition Like a random variable&amp;rsquo;s expectation , the variance is a random variables expected variability. This is the mean squared difference between a random variable and its mean: $$Var(X) = E[(X-E(X))^2]$$.
The notebook view (Matloff) treats $(X-(EX))^2$ as a random variable, s.t. $W=(X-(EX))^2$. The variance of $X$ then is the expected value of $W$, the long-run average value, which is: $$Var(X)=E(g(X))=E(W)=\sum_{c{\in}B}(c)(p(B=c))$$ where $B=g(A)$, the support of $A$ transformed.</description></item><item><title>vector space</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/vector-space/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/vector-space/</guid><description>The resulting set of all possible combinations of vectors made from a smaller subset of vectors.</description></item><item><title>vulnerability</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/vulnerability/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/vulnerability/</guid><description>As a shield Hayley Williams
The necessity of art as catharsis in finding meaning in suffering.
It is our way of owning it, of what Louise Glück mentioned about writing.</description></item><item><title>Wait</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/Poems/Wait/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/Poems/Wait/</guid><description>Wait, for now. Distrust everything if you have to. But trust the hours. Haven&amp;rsquo;t they carried you everywhere, up to now? Personal events will become interesting again. Hair will become interesting. Pain will become interesting. Buds that open out of season will become interesting. Second-hand gloves will become lovely again; their memories are what give them the need for other hands. The desolation of lovers is the same: that enormous emptiness carved out of such tiny beings as we are asks to be filled; the need for the new love is faithfulness to the old.</description></item><item><title>What If Friendship, Not Marriage, Was at the Center of Life</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/relationships/friends-marriage/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/relationships/friends-marriage/</guid><description> Link See also: What Relationships Should Be About</description></item><item><title>What Relationships Should Be About</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/relationships/What-Relationships-Should-Be-About/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/relationships/What-Relationships-Should-Be-About/</guid><description>Many people, after they’ve been in a couple for some time, will privately admit that they are – in many ways – frustrated and disappointed by the person they’ve chosen to share their lives with. If pressed for details, they will have no difficulty coming up with a list: their partner, they might complain:
Is too loyal to their irritating family  doesn’t share their viewsvues on the layout of the living room Never wants to go on camping holidays Plays tennis every Wednesday evening, no matter what Doesn’t like Moroccan food Doesn’t share their enthusiasm for 19th century Russian novels  Has a friend who laughs for no apparent reason Likes doing jigsaws Drinks coffee from a big mug with ‘1984’ inscribed on the side Has a habit of adding ‘actually’ to every second sentence, when it’s actually redundant As the list gets longer, they sigh; they still love their partner and long to be happy together, it’s just that it seems impossibly complicated to make this relationship work.</description></item><item><title>what to talk about on a date</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/relationships/what-to-talk-about-on-a-date/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/relationships/what-to-talk-about-on-a-date/</guid><description>Via school of life Our initial impulse might be to pick up on a current event, some detail of the environment or a few impressive things about our careers. But if a date is at heart an audition for the emotional capacities required for the success of a long-term relationship, the real purpose of conversation must be to try to understand the deep self of the other person. We know we will be doing well if, at a certain point, our date reflects that they’ve never been asked so many psychologically-weighty questions – and are we perhaps some sort of psychotherapist in training…?</description></item><item><title>white matter</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/neuro/white-matter/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/neuro/white-matter/</guid><description>in contrast to gray matter , which consists of neuronal cell bodies, white matter consists of myelinated tracks that facilitate neuronal signaling</description></item><item><title>why do scientists lie</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/Why-Do-Scientists-Lie/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/Why-Do-Scientists-Lie/</guid><description>Abstract: It’s natural to think of scientists as truth seekers, people driven by an intense curiosity to understand the natural world. Yet this picture of scientists and scientific inquiry sits uncomfortably with the reality and prevalence of scientific fraud. If one wants to get at the truth about nature, why lie? Won’t that just set inquiry back, as people pursue false leads? To understand why this occurs – and what can be done about it – we need to understand the *social structures *scientists work within, and how some of the institutions which enable science to be such a successful endeavour all things considered, also abet and encourage fraud.</description></item><item><title>why to memorize poems</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/Poems/why-we-should-memorize-poems/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/Poems/why-we-should-memorize-poems/</guid><description>Article Source Much of our daily lives would be dizzyingly unrecognizable to people living a hundred years ago: what we wear and what we eat, how we travel, how we communicate, how we while away our leisure time. But, surely, our occasional attempts to memorize a poem would feel familiar to them—those inhabitants of a heyday of verse memorization. Little has changed. They, too, in committing a poem to memory, underwent a predictable gamut of frustrations: the pursuit of stubbornly elusive phrases, the inner hammering of rote repetition, tantalizing tip-of-the-tongue stammerings, confident forward marches that finish in an abrupt amnesiac’s cul-de-sac.</description></item><item><title>Why We Go Cold On Our Partners</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/relationships/Why-We-Go-Cold-On-Our-Partners/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/relationships/Why-We-Go-Cold-On-Our-Partners/</guid><description>Source Why We Go Cold on Our Partners The story of the path to coldness in love is well known. We start off full of affection for one another and then – with time – feelings fade. We start prioritising work; we check our phones while they’re speaking; we don’t especially want to hear how their day went.
There’s a populardes populaires surface explanation for this emotional frost: that peoplegens naturally get bored of one another, in the same way as they get bored with everything else – the gadget that once seemed so amazing, the film they used to love… Going cold is, in this story, simply the unavoidable consequence of familiarity.</description></item><item><title>Wild Geese</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/Poems/Wild-Geese/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/Poems/Wild-Geese/</guid><description>You do not have to be good. You do not have to walk on your knees for a hundred miles through the desert repenting. You only have to let the soft animal of your body love what it loves. Tell me about despair, yours, and I will tell you mine. Meanwhile the world goes on. Meanwhile the sun and the clear pebbles of the rain are moving across the landscapes, over the prairies and the deep trees, the mountains and the rivers.</description></item><item><title>Wishing Well</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/Poems/Wishing-Well/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/Poems/Wishing-Well/</guid><description>What’s a chance encounter in a city that’s never left you?
In this Poem the speaker is asked a question by a stranger while standing near the water outside the Metropolitan Museum of Art in New York City. “Pardon me Old School he / says you know is this a wishing well?” He initially brushes off the stranger, but something happens: a shared coin, a well, a wish that is answered as it is made.</description></item><item><title>work</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/work/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/ideas/work/</guid><description/></item><item><title>z-score</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/z-score/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/statistics/z-score/</guid><description>How many standard deviations a particular data point is from the population mean:
$$z=\frac{(x-m)}{\sigma}$$ where $m$ is the population mean and $\sigma$ is the population standard deviation.
If you are looking at particular samples, use $$z_i=\frac{x_i-\bar{x}}{s}$$ where $\bar{x}$ is the sample mean and $s$ is the sample standard deviation.
Further normalization when you have multiple samples leads to
$$z=\frac{(x-m)}{\sigma/\sqrt{n}}$$
which is the standard error of the mean.</description></item></channel></rss>