<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>poetry on</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/tags/poetry/</link><description>Recent content in poetry on</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/tags/poetry/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Wait</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/Poems/Wait/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/Poems/Wait/</guid><description>Wait, for now. Distrust everything if you have to. But trust the hours. Haven&amp;rsquo;t they carried you everywhere, up to now? Personal events will become interesting again. Hair will become interesting. Pain will become interesting. Buds that open out of season will become interesting. Second-hand gloves will become lovely again; their memories are what give them the need for other hands. The desolation of lovers is the same: that enormous emptiness carved out of such tiny beings as we are asks to be filled; the need for the new love is faithfulness to the old.</description></item><item><title>why to memorize poems</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/Poems/why-we-should-memorize-poems/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/Poems/why-we-should-memorize-poems/</guid><description>Article Source Much of our daily lives would be dizzyingly unrecognizable to people living a hundred years ago: what we wear and what we eat, how we travel, how we communicate, how we while away our leisure time. But, surely, our occasional attempts to memorize a poem would feel familiar to them—those inhabitants of a heyday of verse memorization. Little has changed. They, too, in committing a poem to memory, underwent a predictable gamut of frustrations: the pursuit of stubbornly elusive phrases, the inner hammering of rote repetition, tantalizing tip-of-the-tongue stammerings, confident forward marches that finish in an abrupt amnesiac’s cul-de-sac.</description></item><item><title>Wild Geese</title><link>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/Poems/Wild-Geese/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nguyenhphilip.github.io/my-dg/notes/Poems/Wild-Geese/</guid><description>You do not have to be good. You do not have to walk on your knees for a hundred miles through the desert repenting. You only have to let the soft animal of your body love what it loves. Tell me about despair, yours, and I will tell you mine. Meanwhile the world goes on. Meanwhile the sun and the clear pebbles of the rain are moving across the landscapes, over the prairies and the deep trees, the mountains and the rivers.</description></item></channel></rss>